<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Conformity re-asserted in an echo to R.S., or, A return of his VVord to Doctor Womock's asserting 1. That modification of publick worship by personal abilities is not the formal act of the ministerial office, 2. That the ministers of the Church of England ought to submit to the use of an imposed liturgy : and dissolving the objections of Mr. Crofton and R.S. to the contrary / by L.W. ...</title>
            <author>Womock, Laurence, 1612-1685.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 123 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 28 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A66896</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">17949029</idno>
  <idno type="VID">106773</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2264179550</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing W3341</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R38730</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">17949029</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A66896)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 106773)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1112:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Conformity re-asserted in an echo to R.S., or, A return of his VVord to Doctor Womock's asserting 1. That modification of publick worship by personal abilities is not the formal act of the ministerial office, 2. That the ministers of the Church of England ought to submit to the use of an imposed liturgy : and dissolving the objections of Mr. Crofton and R.S. to the contrary / by L.W. ...</title>
                  <author>Womock, Laurence, 1612-1685.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 50 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.G. for Thomas Clark ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1664.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Womock by Wing and NUC pre-1956 imprints.</note>
                  <note>"R.S. may be identified as Ralph Smith, Crofton's publisher and editor"--NUC pre-1956 imprints.</note>
                  <note>"Errata": p. [4].</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Crofton, Zachary, 1625 or 6-1672.</term>
               <term type="personal_name">R. S. --  Word to Doctor Womock.</term>
               <term type="corporate_name">Church of England --  Apologetic works.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Dissenters, Religious --  England --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-12 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-12 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:106773:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:106773:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>CONFORMITY RE-ASSERTED In an Echo to</hi> R. S. <hi>OR, A Return of his VVord to Doctor Womock's ASSERTING,</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>1. That Modification of Publick Worship by personal Abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties is not the formal Act of the Ministerial Office.</item>
                  <item>2. That the Ministers of the Church of <hi>England</hi> ought to submit to the use of an Imposed Liturgy.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>AND <hi>Dissolving the Objections of Mr. CROFTON and</hi> R. S. <hi>to the Contrary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> L.W. D.D. A.S.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Jerubbaal Justified, Page 35.</bibl>
               <p>The Worship of God doth Truly, Formally, and Salvably exist in and by <hi>the English Liturgy.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON: <hi>Printed by</hi> J. G. <hi>for</hi> Thomas Clark <hi>at the South entrance of the</hi> Royal Exchange, 1664.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:106773:2"/>
            <p>IMPRIMATUR:</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Joh: Hall <hi>R. P. D.</hi> Hmfr: Episc. Lond. à Sac. Domest.</signed>
               <date>
                  <hi>Mar.</hi> 9. 1663.</date>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:106773:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen the Doctors Sheets, relating to Mr. <hi>Cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my's</hi> Sermon, were Printed off, there fell into his hands by chance a Book that bare this Title, <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rubbaal Justified.</hi> The pretended Design of this Book, though it cast a sufficient deal of dirt upon the <hi>Establisht Service</hi> of the Church, was to induce the people to frequent it, by proving it to be their Duty to Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate therein, otherwise, the Author affirm'd, they were guilty of the breach of the Fourth Commandement. The Doctor liked the Authors plea for <hi>Communion</hi> well enough. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides the <hi>by-blows</hi> which he gave, in his Discourse, as well to the Establish'd Laws as to those in Authority, and the <hi>Liturgy</hi> it self, the Doctor found he had put forth this Scandalous Positi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Mr. <hi>Croftons</hi> (with his Commendations and a challenge) <hi>viz.</hi> That <hi>no Minister of the Gospel can receive an impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed Liturgy without Sin;</hi> (or to this effect.) The Doctor acquainted a worthy person with it, who having read the <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition</hi> over, with Mr. <hi>Croftons</hi> endeavours to prove the same, he told the Doctor something must needs be returned in Answer to it, and prevailed with him to add those few pages at the end of the Sheets above mentioned, upon this account.</p>
            <p>As the Doctor was unsatisfied with Mr. <hi>Croftons</hi> Positi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, [That no Minister of the Gospel could without sin receive <hi>an imposed Liturgy]</hi> So it seems some <hi>Separatist</hi> was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unsatisfied with <hi>Jerubbaal Justified,</hi> for affirming that the people could not without sin refuse to Communicate <hi>therein.</hi> And this Person having written in Defence of <hi>Separation,</hi> against Mr. <hi>Crofton's</hi> Advocate, as the Doctor had done in Justification of the use of an establish'd <hi>Liturgy</hi> against Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> himself, This provokes <hi>R. S.</hi> (for those are the
<pb facs="tcp:106773:3"/> Letters he desires to be known by) to take up the Cudgels against them both, and puts forth a Pamphlet with this Title, <hi>A Word to Doctor</hi> Womock, <hi>and A Blow (to the Brother of the Separation.)</hi> How the <hi>Separatist</hi> can bear his smart <hi>Blow</hi> I am not much concerned to examine; but of his <hi>Word</hi> to Doctor <hi>Womock</hi> here is a full and strict account as to all the Syllables and Accents of it. That it comes forth no sooner, the reason is, because the Doctor never had the least <hi>hint</hi> of such an Adversary till many moneths after his Pamphlet was dispersed; nor then neither, but casually by the hand of an old acquaintance, to whom some of that Party had privately present<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a Copy, with some insultation at the performance. For what these men are not allow'd to do above board upon the common <hi>stall,</hi> or in the <hi>Pulpit,</hi> they vent under-hand and at <hi>private</hi> Meetings, by those many <hi>Non-Conformists,</hi> who still have and still take all advantages to foment such seeds of <hi>Sedition</hi> and <hi>Schism</hi> as they have formerly sown in the several places where they had been unduly planted. I shall give the Reader no more trouble, after I have desired him to Correct some few Escapes of the Printer, and pass by such as are less Material.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>PAge</hi> 1. <hi>line</hi> 14. <hi>r.</hi> a leading man, <hi>p.</hi> 3. <hi>l.</hi> 19. <hi>r.</hi> give him line, <hi>p.</hi> 17. <hi>l.</hi> 3. <hi>for</hi> action <hi>r.</hi> notion, <hi>p.</hi> 24. <hi>l.</hi> 18. <hi>r.</hi> that will, <hi>p.</hi> 33. <hi>l.</hi> 24. <hi>dele</hi> as.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:106773:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>An Echo to</hi> R. S. <hi>or a Return of his Word to Dr.</hi> Womock.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough <hi>R. S.</hi> be the two first letters of <hi>Rebellion</hi> and <hi>Schism,</hi> we shall not deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine they signifie so much in this place; but leave it to the Mistress of the <hi>ABC</hi> to interpret them. If they stand for the right Name of our <hi>Antagonist,</hi> possibly <hi>R</hi> is the first letter of the last syllable of his <hi>Christian-name,</hi> and then he has held some <hi>mastership</hi> by <hi>Sequestration,</hi> and upon that account has arriv'd at such <hi>dexterity</hi> (as you see) in the art of <hi>Disputation.</hi> He is so well vers'd in the terms of the <hi>Militia,</hi> we may very well conclude him to be a <hi>trading-man</hi> in the black regiment of <hi>Boutefeus,</hi> who made up the <hi>Evangelium Armatum.</hi> How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, we find him a very <hi>waspish</hi> Adversary; he is but <hi>A Word</hi> and <hi>a Blow,</hi> (for so he tells the world in the very <hi>Frontispice</hi> of his <hi>Pamphlet)</hi> though, while he deals his <hi>Blow</hi> to an <hi>Opponent</hi> that sufficiently deserves it, he is so <hi>gentle,</hi> he gives the Doctor but <hi>A Word;</hi> and truly that <hi>Word,</hi> though <hi>loud,</hi> so empty, that if it were not <hi>unsavoury,</hi> it could as little offend as hurt the Doctor.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:106773:4"/>
            <p> By his insolent carriage you may conclude him to be near-allied to the <hi>Pharisee;</hi> for he doth no less admire <hi>him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self</hi> than despise <hi>others;</hi> not onely a <hi>Prelatical</hi> Clergy, (which is not to be wondered at) but his own <hi>brethren</hi> of the <hi>Separation</hi> and the <hi>Covenant;</hi> and this he doth even then when he is pleading for <hi>Non-conformity</hi> to the <hi>Service</hi> and <hi>Orders</hi> of the Church.</p>
            <p>And herein he pretends to <hi>humility</hi> and <hi>modesty,</hi> and speaks demurely of <hi>Conscience</hi> and <hi>the Fear of God;</hi> while he discovers abundance of <hi>pride</hi> and <hi>arrogance,</hi> which (as it hath nothing but a little thin <hi>Sophistry</hi> to support it, so it) betrays him to <hi>prejudice</hi> and <hi>passion, rancour</hi> and <hi>contumely,</hi> against both his <hi>Superiours</hi> and <hi>Informers.</hi> But I shall not suffer my pen to rake into the filthy <hi>ulcers</hi> of this feeble <hi>Lazar,</hi> but content my self with pointing at them as we pass along, that you may take notice of the Infection to avoid it.</p>
            <p>This proud <hi>Philistim</hi> doth <hi>strut</hi> and <hi>advance</hi> himself with his <hi>crest erect,</hi> as if he design'd to <hi>defie all the armies of the living God;</hi> and thus he begins to <hi>crow</hi> and bespeak his victory.</p>
            <p>
               <q>Since my publication of <hi>Jerubbaal justified,</hi> there hath appeared against it, and me, and Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> concerned in it, a double Assault, by two different <hi>Antagonists,</hi> as directly contrary each to the other as the right and left Wing, onely combin'd in one <hi>battalia</hi> under the Prince of darkness <hi>[Behold his charity]</hi> to darken and, if possi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, destroy the truth; so that as <hi>Luther</hi> between <hi>Pope</hi> and <hi>Anabaptist,</hi> stands Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> between a <hi>Prelatical Clergy</hi> and <hi>Separatists:</hi> yet <hi>vincet veritas.</hi>
               </q>
               <hi>[This is a prediction of his own overthrow;</hi> yet he gallops on in tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph, making his <hi>bravadoes</hi> in this language.] <q>Such is the unspeakable weakness of both these mens batteries, that I have passed them with scorn, <hi>[This is his humility]</hi>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:106773:4"/> and stood still in expectation of the on-set of their main Battalia <hi>[Behold his</hi> non-sense; <hi>for whom doth he under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand when he saith this?]</hi> on the one side or on the other; but none appearing, I thought good to check their Insultation <hi>[sed alio fastu]</hi> (with which I hear <hi>[with your harvest ears]</hi> they are puffed up) by these few lines And first, to begin with the learned Doctor, I would crave leave to tell him, if he will give good assurance that he will in the Schools of the University give Mr. <hi>Crofton (viva voce)</hi> the Answer published in his name, I will be bound <hi>[What, by your Solemn League and Covenant?]</hi> Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> shall meet him to receive it, and <hi>[Enter Impertinence and Vanity]</hi> if the Boys do not hiss the Doctor, he shall go out <hi>victor.</hi>
               </q> By which discourse a man might wager that he held his <hi>wit</hi> as well as his <hi>mastership</hi> by Sequestration, and the <hi>tide</hi> being now turn'd, he is quite <hi>outed</hi> of them both. But let us give him time.</p>
            <p>
               <q>Shall I presume (saith he) to take a turn with this reverend Archdeacon? I must then tell him, if he did not mistake, his Printer hath wrong'd him at the entrance of his Undertaking, to make him read <hi>Non-conformist</hi> instead of <hi>Now-conformist.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>A very remarkable Observation! but the Doctor was aware of the distinction, and so the mistake is imputable to the <hi>Compositor</hi> or the <hi>Corrector</hi> of the Press. But this advantage will not get <hi>R. S.</hi> the victory, for it is nothing to the purpose; and therefore he wheels about, and char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges again in these lines.</p>
            <p>
               <q>That <hi>pride and overweening conceit of our own worth maketh men Non conformists,</hi> I deny; for it is <hi>humility</hi> and <hi>the fear of the Lord;</hi> They dare not deviate from Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine directions, and your instance is an evidence of the same; whilest Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> doth humbly consult whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:106773:5"/> his <hi>Conformity</hi> may consist with his <hi>Ministerial Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice,</hi> and modestly offer his Notions to Argumentation; the one sheweth his <hi>fear of sin,</hi> whilest the other shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his <hi>willingness to be convinced,</hi> and both his <hi>hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Here, Mr. <hi>Replicant,</hi> you talk of the <hi>fear of the Lord</hi> and the <hi>fear of sin;</hi> and if you could name but one single per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of your persuasion (and, if you consult your own bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>som, you dare not be so arrogant as to make your self the Instance) that was not heartily engaged in the late <hi>rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion,</hi> you might have some colour to be believed: But some of you will pretend, that God <hi>puts his fear into your hearts</hi> by an <hi>omnipotent</hi> operation, and then that fear acts you <hi>irresistibly,</hi> and consequently whether you run into <hi>Schism</hi> or <hi>Sedition,</hi> or any other crime, you do all <hi>in the fear of God,</hi> and you cannot do otherwise. But if you fear <hi>sin,</hi> 'tis at the same rate with those <hi>blind guides, which</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 23. 24.</note>
               <hi>strain at a gnat and swallow a camel.</hi> Do you fear <hi>sin,</hi> who are not afraid <hi>to speak evil of dignities?</hi> You may pretend <note place="margin">2 Pet. 2. 10.</note> to be afraid of a <hi>Liturgy</hi> imposed by your Kings <hi>command,</hi> but you are not afraid of <hi>a Covenant</hi> imposed against his <hi>Authority.</hi> You are afraid to have your shoulders in a <hi>Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plice,</hi> but you are not afraid to have your hands in <hi>bloud.</hi> And yet you make the world believe, such is your <hi>fear of the Lord,</hi> you <hi>dare not deviate from Divine directions:</hi> But is not this one of the Divine directions, <hi>Obey them that</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 13. 17.</note>
               <hi>have the rule over you, and submit your selves; for they watch for your souls as they that must give an account.</hi> And this, <hi>We command you in the name of our Lord Jesus Christ, that</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Thes. 3. 6.</note>
               <hi>ye withdraw your selves from every brother that walketh disor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly, and not after the tradition which he hath received of us.</hi> Do not you <hi>deviate</hi> from these <hi>directions?</hi> Impudence it self cannot deny it without blushing. Whom Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> consulted in this case I know not: but when men do <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pannel</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:106773:5"/> their fellows upon the <hi>jury</hi> to inquire into their mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demeanours, they expect a more favourable <hi>verdict</hi> than to be found guilty. That <hi>notions</hi> may be offered to <hi>argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation</hi> rather out of <hi>pride</hi> than any desire to receive <hi>sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction,</hi> you are not to learn; and we cannot discover over-much modesty in the papers that either he or you have offered to the world: but if there be that <hi>humility</hi> and <hi>willingness</hi> to be convinced which you pretend to, a little time will shew it. But it begets a <hi>vehement</hi> suspicion you are not <hi>ingenuous,</hi> when you use such <hi>Sophistry</hi> to blind the true state of the <hi>question,</hi> and impose upon your unwary Reader, as we shall observe (with your <hi>contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons)</hi> in your discourse following.</p>
            <p>
               <q>His position (saith <hi>R. S.)</hi> you have truly transcribed, and observed the <hi>state</hi> thereof, <hi>[so you confess]</hi> but <hi>[you say]</hi> if to affirm, <hi>It cannot be denied to be a most base and slavish servility to prostitute the Office to which we are apted and ordained</hi> by the Lord Jesus Christ <hi>unto the pleasure and prescriptions of men, though the best for Quality and Authority,</hi> be to be proud, I will be proud, <hi>[You say, and I believe you whether so or otherwise]</hi> and glory in my pride: And I doubt not, if you were calendered as a man who should deny this Position, you, Sir, would be found proud enough to declare your displeasure, as unjustly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proched. <hi>[How much of truth is in this your presumption we shall see anon; but you adde]</hi> I therefore soberly require you to deny it if you can or dare; <hi>[you are a bold cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pion]</hi> and if you cannot, what meaneth this digressive flourish?</q>
               <hi>[I desire the</hi> Reader <hi>by the way to take notice how this</hi> Replicant <hi>contradicts himself for want of a good memory; for what he calls here</hi> a digressive flourish, <hi>after a few lines (to serve his own turn) he makes to be the very</hi> question in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate: <hi>but he goes on thus,]</hi>
               <q>Your <hi>flourish</hi> indeed hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven you the <hi>start,</hi> so that you have <hi>lost</hi> your <hi>question,</hi>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:106773:6"/> and fall on a <hi>magisterial Swada [with a</hi> w] of Mr. <hi>Crof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons</hi> Conformity: Which of Mr. <hi>Croftons</hi> Syllogisms do you hereby shake? Is not this fair disputing?</q> To this I answer, That the <hi>onely</hi> Argument which the Doctor had not formerly shaken all to pieces in other of his Papers <note n="*" place="margin">Pulpit-Concepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons Popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Decep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, <hi>per totum.</hi>
               </note>, he undertook to dispute in these; and sure as this is a way to avoid needless repetitions, so 'tis a course of <hi>fair disputing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But <hi>R. S.</hi> proceeds and tells the Doctor, <q>
                  <hi>We will weigh your Reason:</hi> You say, Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> may please to be so humble as <hi>to condescend</hi> to such an <hi>Imposition</hi> for <hi>peace</hi> and <hi>orders</hi> sake.</q> And then he falls into a <hi>convulsion</hi> and <hi>ecstacy,</hi> and cries out, <hi>[How! condescend to</hi> such an Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition <hi>which</hi> prostituteth the Office received from <hi>Christ</hi> to the pleasure of men? <hi>Can you desire it? were you in earnest when you wrote this? can you judge it an act of humility, or not rather the greatest arrogancy,</hi> for Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> instead of <hi>Minister of Jesus Christ</hi> to write <hi>a Minister of Men?]</hi> Thus he raves he knows not why; and if he be not out of his <hi>wits,</hi> I am sure he is out of his <hi>Logick.</hi> A fallacy, <hi>Ignora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio Elenchi,</hi> hath brought him into this <hi>paroxism</hi> and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stemper; for the <hi>position</hi> (against which the Doctor com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates) is this, (and this <hi>Replicant</hi> doth in cool bloud ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge that the Doctor hath truly transcribed it, and observed the state thereof) <hi>That</hi> stated Forms <hi>for the cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bration of solemn publick worship, and the several parts thereof,</hi> composed, digested, <hi>and (for the very</hi> words, terms, <hi>and</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressions <hi>thereof)</hi> determined <hi>and</hi> prescribed <hi>by some others than the</hi> Parson <hi>or</hi> Minister, <hi>who standeth to minister Gods</hi> Ordinances <hi>between God and his Church;</hi> such an <hi>imposed Liturgy</hi> Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> cannot without sin <hi>submit</hi> unto. This is clearly Mr. <hi>Croftons</hi> Position, and when he grows warm in pursuing the proof of it, he lets his passions loose into <note place="margin">Position, pag. 3.</note> declamation, and saith, <hi>[It cannot be denied to be a most
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:106773:6"/> base and slavish servility, to prostitute the Office to which we are adapted and ordained by the Lord Jesus Christ, unto the pleasure and prescriptions of men, though the best for Quality and Authority.]</hi> From which <hi>insolent</hi> Assertion the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor did argue, that Pride had a strong hand in the manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of this contention; and endeavouring to becalm Mr. <hi>Croftons</hi> passions, he attempted to prove him obliged to condescend to such an Imposition (of <hi>Liturgy,</hi> as was formerly mentioned, and is the true state of the Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versie) <hi>for peace and orders sake;</hi> and the Doctors Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was this:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>What I may lawfully be determined to by my own private judgment, that I may lawfully be determined to by the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of my Superiours:</hi> But <hi>to stated forms for the celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Gods solemn publick worship, composed, (and for the very words, terms and expressions) digested into method, I may lawfully be determined by my own private judgment:</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>to stated forms for the celebration of Gods solemn publick worship, composed and (for the very words, terms and expressi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons) digested into method, I may lawfully be determined by the judgment of my Superiours.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here the <hi>Replicant</hi> having lost sight of the Question himself, or rather wilfully mistaken it, runs out into ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postulation with the Doctor after this manner; <q>But how now Mr. Doctor? what is become of your Question? do you not use to bring that into your Conclusion? that Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> ought to condescend to <hi>such an Imposition</hi> which <hi>prostituteth the Office received from Christ to the pleasure of men,</hi> was that you pretended to prove; doth not your Syllogism want a foot more to make it reach? But to play with the <hi>prevaricator,</hi> know (Sir) I deny both the Propositions of your well-form'd Syllogism.</q>
            </p>
            <p>But now, Mr. <hi>Replicant,</hi> give me leave to take a turn with you in your vein of Expostulation. Do not you play
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:106773:7"/> the <hi>Impostor,</hi> thus to <hi>disguise</hi> your self, and <hi>palliate</hi> your <hi>disobedience</hi> to the well-settled <hi>Ord<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rs</hi> of the Church, by calling that which is your <hi>duty</hi> by an ugly name, <hi>A prosti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of your Office received from Christ to the pleasures of men?</hi> And do not you know that the Doctor alleged the said passage from Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> not as <hi>the state of the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion,</hi> (which you confess he had <hi>truly observed)</hi> but as a proof of the <hi>pride</hi> of those that contend about it; for which reason you call it a <hi>digressive flourish.</hi> If the <hi>question</hi> had been this, <hi>Whether that expression had been a sufficient ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument of their pride?</hi> I confess the Doctors Syllogism had not been concluding, because defective; but the question being about <hi>stated Forms,</hi> and <hi>that</hi> truly transcribed and observed by the Doctor, as you acknowledge, you play the <hi>prevaricator</hi> your self, (which is something more than playing <hi>with</hi> him) and the <hi>Impostor</hi> too, thus to use <hi>falla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies</hi> to delude your Reader. But having done this, you exercise a little ingenuity towards the Doctor in telling him his Syllogism is a <hi>well-form'd</hi> Syllogism, though you manfully deny both the Propositions of it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. You deny the <hi>minor</hi> Proposition, <hi>viz.</hi> That <hi>to sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Forms for celebration of Gods solemn publick worship, composed and (for the very words, terms and expressions) di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gested into method, I may lawfully be determined by mine own private judgment.]</hi> This he denies. But how now, Mr. <hi>Replicant?</hi> May I not be determined by <hi>my own private judgment?</hi> How doth this <hi>cotten</hi> with your Answer to the <hi>major,</hi> (a little after) where you discourse thus? <hi>[Mine own eye is the best guide of mine own steps; mine own under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing is my</hi> candle <hi>from the Lord; my dim light,</hi> judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um rationale, <hi>shineth brighter in the closet of mine own breast than</hi> 400. <hi>candles, or the</hi> forense judicium <hi>of a Convocation;</hi> (and a little after) <hi>I will move by mine own eye, be it never so weak, and my Superiours never so strong; though my dim light
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:106773:7"/> seeth not more, it seeth more truly and more directively than their brighter.]</hi> Thus the <hi>Replicant</hi> preacheth in commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of his <hi>own private judgment,</hi> when he is returning an Answer to the <hi>major;</hi> but <hi>now,</hi> that he is concerned to say otherwise, <hi>(right or wrong)</hi> he finds this his <hi>candle from the Lord</hi> to be such an <hi>Ignis fatuus,</hi> that he saith, in this case he cannot lawfully be <hi>determined</hi> by it.</p>
            <p>Were this <hi>Replicant</hi> true to his own Principles, we need go no further for a proof of this Proposition than his own Affirmations; but because he plays <hi>fast and loose</hi> with his Answers, we shall evince the truth of our Proposition by this Argument; <hi>To stated Forms for celebration of Gods so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn worship I must be determined, either immediately by the Authority of God himself, or by the Prescription of my Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours, or by the resolution of my Equals and Inferiours, or by my own private judgment.</hi> I cannot expect the <hi>first;</hi> no man, that is well in his wits, will now pretend to <hi>divine re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation</hi> to determine his particular <hi>forms</hi> of prayer; and the <hi>Replicant</hi> will not allow of the <hi>second,</hi> the <hi>prescriptions</hi> of our <hi>Superiours</hi> to this effect; and that we should be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined by the <hi>Resolutions</hi> of our <hi>Equals</hi> or <hi>Inferiours,</hi> I am sure is much more unreasonable than the former: It follows therefore, That (unless we stand to the courtesie of some Familiar Spirit to suggest the Form to us) we must be determined herein by our own private judgment, or else remain for ever undetermined.</p>
            <p>But the truth is, though <hi>R. S.</hi> finds himself concerned to keep a close Guard, and for that reason denies the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position; yet he does it upon such a ground as doth clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly yield it; for, he saith, Though Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> doth not exclude <hi>his own judgment when he pleads for the liberty of his own invention to compose</hi> and <hi>modifie</hi> his own <hi>forms</hi> of <hi>pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick worship,</hi> yet he denieth his judgment a <hi>power</hi> to <hi>deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine a stated Form,</hi> semper eadem, <hi>always the same, for
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:106773:8"/> words, terms</hi> and <hi>expressions,</hi> whatever be the <hi>variations</hi> of Gods <hi>providence</hi> and the Churches <hi>condition.]</hi> Here, I say, he doth grant the Proposition which he offers to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny: For 1. in this case, doth not the <hi>private judgment</hi> still determine the <hi>form</hi> according to the <hi>variation</hi> of provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences and conditions? What is it else that doth deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine him, for <hi>words, terms</hi> and <hi>expressions,</hi> upon those <hi>va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious</hi> occasions? And 2. the Doctors <hi>argument</hi> is not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strained to <hi>one</hi> single <hi>form,</hi> semper eadem, <hi>always the same,</hi> whatever be the <hi>variations</hi> of Gods providence and the Churches condition: The Doctor argues for <hi>Forms</hi> in the <hi>plural</hi> number, and our <hi>Superiours</hi> have furnished us with <hi>variety,</hi> (and can adde more) according to the <hi>variation</hi> of providences. Besides the <hi>ordinary Service,</hi> with <hi>occasio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Collects,</hi> is there not an <hi>Office</hi> for the 5. of <hi>November,</hi> and another for the 29. of <hi>May,</hi> yea and one for the 30. of <hi>January</hi> too? we may thank such as you for the <hi>occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion,</hi> while we <hi>praise</hi> God for the <hi>blessings</hi> commemorated in <hi>them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But let us attend the march of this great Champion: <hi>[Nor doth this any way follow</hi> (saith he) <hi>on the use of his judgment in managing his liberty. That a man may judge a Crutch fit for his own condition, will not conclude that he may</hi> sanâ mente <hi>confine himself to a Crutch, one and the same Crutch, at all times in all conditions: This argumentation is a manifest halting before a Creeple. In the last, the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment must needs be erroneous, to be corrected before it be obeyed.]</hi> To as much of this discourse as is <hi>intelligible</hi> I answer, That if the <hi>Cripple</hi> acteth <hi>sanâ mente,</hi> it is his own judgment that determines him, <hi>what crutch</hi> is fit for his condition, and <hi>at what time,</hi> and <hi>upon what occasion</hi> he should use it; and that is enough to verifie the truth of our Proposition against his groundless denial of it. If he lays aside his Crutch before he can walk stedfastly with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:106773:8"/> it, or change it for a worse, then he doth not act <hi>sanâ mente,</hi> he is not determined by his judgment, but follows the wild rovings of a <hi>giddy</hi> fancy like a <hi>frantick</hi> person.</p>
            <p>But I find our <hi>Replicant</hi> begins to <hi>halt,</hi> and is like to come <hi>lamely</hi> off in his <hi>answer</hi> to this Proposition; and therefore for pity-sake I will not take his <hi>crutch</hi> from him, though it stands him in no stead, but to help a very <hi>little wit</hi> to bring in an old <hi>proverb</hi> to as little purpose; nor will I meddle with his <hi>non-sense</hi> in these words, <hi>[In the last, the judgment must needs be erroneous, to be corrected before it be obeyed]</hi> but pass on presently to the proof of the <hi>major,</hi> viz. <hi>What I may lawfully be determined to by my own private judgment, that I may lawfully be determined to by the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of my Superiours.</hi> This our <hi>Replicant</hi> doth deny, and it is thus enforced;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>What I may lawfully be determined to by a weaker judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to that I may lawfully be determined by a judgment that is stronger. But to stated Forms &amp;c. I may lawfully be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined by a weaker judgment,</hi> viz. <hi>mine own.</hi> Ergo <hi>to sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Forms, &amp;c. I may lawfully be determined by a judgment that is stronger,</hi> viz. <hi>my Superiours.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What saith the <hi>Replicant</hi> to this Argument? <hi>[Here, Sir,</hi> (saith he) <hi>to make the Auditors laugh, I will again be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come</hi> ridiculous <hi>in your fancy, and deny both your Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitions.]</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here the man deals very honestly, and is as good as his word; for doth not he become <hi>ridiculous</hi> that talks of a <hi>sequel</hi> in a plain <hi>categorical</hi> Proposition? And is not he worthy to be <hi>laugh'd at,</hi> who in the repetition of a Syllo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gism makes <hi>four</hi> Terms where he finds but <hi>three?</hi> and so does he; for he s<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ith, [I deny the <hi>major</hi> in the sequel, <hi>I may be determined by the weaker judgment;</hi> and it will not thence follow, <hi>that I</hi> must <hi>therefore be determined by the stronger judgment.]</hi> Here the <hi>Replicant</hi> turns <hi>[may]</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:106773:9"/>
               <hi>[must],</hi> which makes a considerable difference in the Proposition: but let him make his best advantage of it; and thus I answer, If I may be determined by the <hi>lesser</hi> light or judgment rather than the stronger, then either because it is <hi>less,</hi> or because it is <hi>mine own.</hi> Not the <hi>first,</hi> because it is <hi>less;</hi> for if so, then the <hi>Jews</hi> had better means to determine them than the <hi>Christians,</hi> and the <hi>Gentiles</hi> than the <hi>Jews,</hi> and we should be concern'd to <hi>grow,</hi> not in <hi>knowledge,</hi> but in <hi>ignorance.</hi> This our <hi>Repli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant</hi> dares not affirm. The reason then why I may be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined by the <hi>lesser light</hi> or <hi>weaker judgment</hi> is, because it is <hi>my own;</hi> and <hi>[mine own eye is the best guide of my own steps, though I see but darkly,</hi> (saith our Antagonist:) <hi>my own understanding is my candle from the Lord; my dim light,</hi> judicium rationale, <hi>shineth brighter in the closet of mine own breast, than</hi> 400. <hi>candles, or the</hi> forense judicium <hi>of a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation.]</hi> Thus our <hi>Replicant</hi> in one breath, 1. <hi>mistakes</hi> the <hi>question,</hi> and 2. <hi>imposeth</hi> upon the <hi>Reader,</hi> and 3. <hi>inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feres</hi> with Gods holy <hi>word</hi> and <hi>ordinance.</hi> First, he <hi>mistakes</hi> the <hi>question</hi> here, which is, <hi>whether a man may be determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by his</hi> own weaker <hi>light rather than the</hi> greater <hi>light of his Superiours?</hi> But he tells us, his own <hi>dim</hi> light, his <hi>judicium rationale,</hi> shines brighter in the closet of his <hi>own</hi> bosom, than 400. candles, or the <hi>judicium forense</hi> of a <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation;</hi> and so in <hi>contradiction</hi> to his own assertion he is determined not by the <hi>lesser</hi> light but the <hi>greater,</hi> not by the <hi>weaker</hi> judgment but the <hi>stronger.</hi> I'le adde but this; If he <hi>confines</hi> his eyes to his <hi>own dim</hi> light, and <hi>shuts</hi> his closet-doors to keep out the light of the <hi>Sun,</hi> or those 400. <hi>candles,</hi> he deserves to walk on in <hi>darkness.</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, he goes about to <hi>impose</hi> upon his <hi>Reader,</hi> by his comparison of a <hi>corporal</hi> and a <hi>spiritual</hi> eye; for though mine <hi>own</hi> eye be the best guide of my own steps to the <hi>bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,</hi> yet it is not so to the <hi>soul.</hi> That promise of the Lord,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:106773:9"/>
               <hi>I will guide thee with mine eye,</hi> hath matter of an higher comfort in it. This will appear further by the evidence that, Thirdly, he doth <hi>interfere</hi> with Gods holy <hi>word</hi> and <hi>ordinance:</hi> For 1. <hi>that self-denial</hi> which the Gospel calls for doth extend (and not without reason) to <hi>pertinacy</hi> in our <hi>opinions;</hi> and if there be not some kind of <hi>mortifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of our own carnal judgments, we shall many times be tempted to cry out against the Orders of our Superiours, in as great a transportation as <hi>Naaman</hi> did in another case, <hi>Are not Abana and Pharpar rivers of Damascus better than</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 King. 5. 12</note>
               <hi>all the waters of Israel? may I not wash in them and be clean?</hi> But why are we forbid to be <hi>wise in our own conceits,</hi> and to <note place="margin">Ro. 12. 16. Prov 3. 5, 7</note>
               <hi>lean to our own understanding,</hi> and commanded to be <hi>wise unto sobriety?</hi> It was the saying as well as the observation of a <hi>wise</hi> and <hi>pious</hi> person <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Qui se sibi magnistrum constituit, stuito se di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scipulum subdit.</hi> Bern. epist. 87.</note>, <hi>He that is his own scholar, hath a fool to his master:</hi> and <hi>Solomons</hi> meaning is the same when he saith, <note n="*" place="margin">Pro. 26. 12.</note>
               <hi>Seest thou a man that is wise in his own conceit? there is more hope of a fool than of him.</hi> And now, Mr. <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicant,</hi> you may <hi>walk in the light of your fire, and in the sparks that you have kindled;</hi> but remember there is a <hi>Wo</hi>
               <note place="margin">Isa, 50. 11.</note> denounced against those that are <hi>wise in their own eyes:</hi> and <note place="margin">Isa. 5. 21.</note> therefore retract the arrogance of that expression in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parison of your Superiours, <hi>[Though my dim light seeth not</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>A Word,</hi> pag. 4.</note>
               <hi>more, it seeth more truly and more directively than their brighter.]</hi> This shews no great willingness to be convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced. For 2. this doth <hi>interfere</hi> with Gods holy <hi>ordinance;</hi> for why did he set up a <hi>candlestick</hi> and provide <hi>lights</hi> in his Church? why does he make it the peoples duty to <hi>seek the law at the Priests lips?</hi> why did he command, <hi>Obey them that have the rule over you, and submit your selves?</hi> why did God make that promise, and instance in it as such a <hi>signal</hi> blessing, <hi>Thine eyes shall see thy teachers?</hi> After all <note place="margin">Isa. 30. 20.</note>
               <hi>this provision,</hi> these <hi>commands</hi> and <hi>promises,</hi> must every man be allowed to be his own <hi>guide,</hi> and to <hi>do what is right <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ibid.</hi> 21.</note>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:106773:10"/> in his own eyes?</hi> 'Tis not the light <hi>within</hi> thee, but the voice <hi>behind</hi> thee, (and that may be <hi>the voice of the rod</hi> too, the most proper instrument to be used upon them that turn their <hi>backs</hi> upon their <hi>governours)</hi> that is design<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Almighty God to reduce such as turn out of the way <hi>to the right hand or to the left.</hi> And seeing this is Gods ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged <hi>institution</hi> and <hi>ordinance,</hi> be not faithless, but <hi>Trust in the Lord with all thy heart, and lean not to thine own understanding.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 3. 5.</note>
            </p>
            <p>But you instance, [The learned <hi>Davenant</hi> hath taught me, <hi>Men may guide us</hi> judicio ministeriali; <hi>but every one must judge</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, judicio privato &amp; practicae discretionis: <hi>Yea, he hath concluded</hi> (you say) <hi>ad nudam praescriptionem aut determinationem alterius, sine lumine pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vati judicii, nemo est qui credere potest, etiamsi cupiat ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ximè.]</hi> But who doth debar you the use of your <hi>judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> of <hi>discretion?</hi> or who requires from you a <hi>brutish</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequiousness to their <hi>naked prescriptions and determinations</hi> without reason? If you value the <hi>judgment</hi> and <hi>piety</hi> of that learned <hi>Prelate,</hi> why do you not <hi>follow</hi> it in your <hi>pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice?</hi> Certainly in matters <hi>doubtful</hi> and <hi>indifferent</hi> he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solves, that every mans <hi>discretion</hi> should determine him to subscribe to the <hi>judgment</hi> and <hi>orders</hi> of his <hi>Superiours.</hi> You cannot be ignorant of his constant <hi>practice</hi> in point of <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy;</hi> and for the <hi>Ceremonies</hi> in use amongst us, you have his <hi>Determination</hi> out of the <hi>Chair</hi> as Professor, which <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deter. <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 20. <hi>p.</hi> 101.</note> concludes thus; <hi>Sive igitur</hi> potestatem obligantis, <hi>sive</hi> qualitatem ceremoniarum, <hi>sive</hi> modum obligationis <hi>specte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, Eccl<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>sia Anglicana justissimè obligat ad ceremonias.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But from the <hi>major R. S.</hi> proceeds to deny the <hi>minor,</hi> viz. That <hi>to stated Forms, &amp;c. I may lawfully be determined by a weaker judgment,</hi> (viz.) <hi>my own.</hi> But, Sir, saith this <hi>Replicant</hi> to the Doctor, <hi>that you may know</hi> a man of intolerable pride, <hi>in your account, I deny your</hi> Minor, and tell
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:106773:10"/> you in general, <hi>That the private judgment of a single person may be stronger than the judgment of a Convocation or whole Council.]</hi> But this Answer doth not contradict the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors Proposition, and therefore it is nothing to the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose. But besides, the <hi>Replicant</hi> may remember an old Axiom in the Schools, <hi>A posse ad esse non valet conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quentia:</hi> his <hi>may-be's</hi> are not <hi>cogent</hi> arguments ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily: <hi>Plus vident duo quàm unus oculus;</hi> which may be rendered in the words of <hi>Solomon, In the multitude of coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sellours</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov 11. 1<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 24. 6.</note>
               <hi>there is safety.</hi> But he proceeds to instance, <hi>[Have you never read of one</hi> Gamaliel <hi>in the Convocation</hi> (but why not rather the ASSEMBLY?) <hi>of the Scribes and Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risees? or of one</hi> Cranmer <hi>in the</hi> Six-Articles Council <hi>of King</hi> Henry <hi>the Eighth? or of one</hi> Paphnutius <hi>in the Council of</hi> Nice?] Well, we have read of these persons; but what then? For <hi>Cranmer,</hi> though but a <hi>single</hi> person, yet he was an <hi>Archbishop;</hi> and you should do well to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber <hi>that</hi> for the honour of that <hi>Order;</hi> and yet that is but <hi>one</hi> example, and <hi>One Swallow will not make a Summer;</hi> nor can you make <hi>fair weather,</hi> to adorn your pretensions, of your other Instances; for the text tells you, that <hi>all</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 5.</note>
               <hi>the Council</hi> agreed to <hi>Gamaliel,</hi> (and some one single per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son must break the <hi>ice</hi> in every debate:) and yet should those in Authority prove so very <hi>Jews,</hi> as to deny Christ to be the <hi>Messias,</hi> and silence the <hi>holy Gospel,</hi> you may be allowed to be singular in your <hi>zele,</hi> and start up the <hi>Gama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liel</hi> in the <hi>Convocation</hi> of Scribes and Pharisees. For <hi>Paphnutius,</hi> I wonder you should set his <hi>single</hi> judgment in opposition to that whole <hi>Council;</hi> for though he <hi>first</hi> took up the <hi>debate,</hi> yet the story tells us, the <hi>whole Council</hi> concurr'd with him in that business.</p>
            <p>I could (were I so disposed) tell you of <hi>John of Leiden, Hacket,</hi> and other (of your <hi>self magnifying Lights)</hi> Heads of <hi>pernicious Factions,</hi> and so give you a <hi>Rowland</hi> for your
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:106773:11"/>
               <hi>Oliver;</hi> but I desire you at least to remember, that it was the <hi>Fathers</hi> of the Church in <hi>council</hi> that blasted the most <hi>damnable heresies</hi> that were broched from time to time by <hi>single Presbyters,</hi> or others.</p>
            <p>But <hi>R. S.</hi> goes on, and tells the Doctor, <hi>If</hi> (you have) <hi>not</hi> (read of <hi>Paphnutius,</hi> and the rest) <hi>give us leave to tell you, we hope you will not from</hi> Archdeacon <hi>rise to be</hi> Archbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop; <hi>which if you should, we should fear to be forced to pluck out our eyes, because you say they are weaker than yours, now you are set above us. Let, Sir,</hi> junior Soph. <hi>judge whether you have not disputed like the master of much reason.]</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But, good Mr. <hi>R. S.</hi> whatever indignation you have to the <hi>Archdeacon,</hi> you should not slander him; he no where saith (as you suggest) <hi>that your eyes are weaker than his now he is set above you;</hi> but this he must say, that there are some <hi>set</hi> as well above <hi>himself</hi> as <hi>you</hi> who are very much more <hi>quick-sighted</hi> than you <hi>both;</hi> and I hope <hi>he</hi> is so charitable, <hi>he</hi> would not <hi>pluck out your eyes,</hi> but <hi>open</hi> them, that having the like <hi>apprehensions</hi> of <hi>it</hi> with <hi>himself,</hi> you may be induced to <hi>comply</hi> with him in your <hi>submission</hi> to <hi>their</hi> Authority. For <hi>they</hi> doubtless have the advantage of <hi>situation,</hi> and are <hi>nearer</hi> to Almighty God in <hi>place;</hi> and if that signifies nothing, the <hi>promises</hi> of Gods <hi>assistance</hi> to men in <hi>office</hi> are of none effect.</p>
            <p>But <hi>R. S.</hi> resolves now to be honest: he tells the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor, <hi>[I will give you your due, you do strike at the</hi> principle <hi>which is the</hi> radix <hi>of Mr.</hi> Croftons <hi>argumentation;]</hi> but withall he adds, that the Doctor is <hi>no skilful Carpenter,</hi> his <hi>blow</hi> doth neither <hi>reach the root</hi> nor <hi>shake the tree;</hi> and thus he proves it, <q>[Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> argues, <hi>Ministerial modification of publick worship by personal abilities, is the formal act of the Ministerial office;</hi> and he puts his <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spondent</hi> to assign any other: You (the Doctor, saith he) most profoundly answer by denial, and then assign <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stration
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:106773:11"/> to be the formal act of the Ministerial office.</hi> Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> I know (say you) will admit your <hi>action</hi> in the <hi>genus;</hi> an inferiour Minister of State or servant in a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily must minister as well as a Minister of the Gospel; but that <hi>specifical</hi> act which shall difference <hi>the special mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistrations of these special relations and several capacities,</hi> was the thing inquired; and what is the <hi>formalis ratio</hi> of the Ministerial office in <hi>the ministration of solemn publick worship,</hi> is the question. To tell us, <hi>Ministration is the formal act of Ministration,</hi> is good Scepticism; <hi>Dolosus versatur in generalibus:</hi> the <hi>formal act</hi> of the Ministerial office is to <hi>minister,</hi> but <hi>quomodo?</hi> is the question. To hold your Lord Bishops stirrup, or the candle to an Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deacon, will not sure <hi>fulfill the Ministry</hi> of a Gospel-Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister; yet it is <hi>ministration.]</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Thus <hi>R. S. rants</hi> at the Doctor and the <hi>Hierarchy</hi> of the Church, as if the <hi>Covenant</hi> were yet in force, and an <hi>Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance</hi> for their eradication. Were I willing to return his <hi>sarcasm</hi> I would ask him this question, Whether a less pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance than <hi>holding the Bishops stirrup</hi> can be inflicted upon persons that have been so violen to throw their Lordships out of the <hi>saddle?</hi> and do not they deserve to hold a <hi>candle</hi> to an <hi>Archdeacon,</hi> who have so long held one to the <hi>Devil</hi> to compass their designs? But I shall spare them, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply my discourse to the Exceptions of this <hi>Replicant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And first, whereas he excepts against the Doctor for saying that <hi>Ministration is the formal act of Ministration;</hi> this, I say, is false and groundless. 1. False; for the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor did not tell him that <hi>Ministration is the formal act of Ministration,</hi> but that <hi>to minister</hi> was the <hi>formal act</hi> of the <hi>Ministerial office.</hi> And therefore 2. his Exception is groundless <note n="*" place="margin">It is a rule in Logick, <hi>Ta<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>, <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>n<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> praedicata, qualia pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>untur esse subjecta.</hi>
               </note>; for take <hi>[ministration]</hi> or <hi>[to minister]</hi> one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in that <hi>latitude</hi> and with the same <hi>limitation</hi> as <hi>Ministe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial office</hi> is taken in Mr. <hi>Croftons</hi> Position, (when he saith,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:106773:12"/>
               <hi>An imposed Liturgy is destructive to the formal act of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisterial office)</hi> and his pretended <hi>scepticism</hi> is vanished; here is then as little room for this <hi>Dolosus</hi> to dance in, as for his <hi>cavil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But whereas 2. he defines <hi>the formal act of the Ministerial office</hi> to be <hi>the ministerial modification</hi> of publick worship <hi>by personal abilities.]</hi> To this I answer,</p>
            <p>1. If by <hi>ministerial modification</hi> of <hi>publick worship</hi> he had meant onely the <hi>performance</hi> of the <hi>duties</hi> of publick wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship; then I should have told him, <hi>those duties</hi> are performed <hi>by personal abilities</hi> in the use of an <hi>imposed Liturgy.</hi> The <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding, will</hi> and <hi>affections,</hi> as they are required by Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God, so are they <hi>imployed</hi> and <hi>exercised</hi> in such an <hi>imposed</hi> Service. If the Priest reads the <hi>Forms</hi> out of a book, his <hi>eyes</hi> are his own; if he takes the pains to get them with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out book, (which is more pains than to pour out such as the <hi>Fancy</hi> shall suggest <hi>extempore)</hi> his <hi>memory</hi> is his own; and so he performs the <hi>duty</hi> by his <hi>own personal abilities.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But by <hi>modification of publick worship</hi> he means the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate composition of Forms for publick worship, and by his own <hi>personal abilities</hi> this <hi>Replicant</hi> understands principally the exercise of his <hi>Invention;</hi> for his words are these, [Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> doth not exclude <hi>his own judgment</hi> when he pleads <hi>for the liberty of his own Invention to compose and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>difie his forms of publick worship.]</hi> He saith, <hi>he doth not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude his judgment,</hi> but it is <hi>the liberty of his Invention he pleads for.</hi> Yes forsooth, these are the <hi>shrines</hi> that bring <note place="margin">Acts 19. 24.</note> no small gains to these <hi>craftsmen;</hi> and <hi>they</hi> must contend for the <hi>liberty</hi> of their own <hi>Invention</hi> to make such <hi>shrines</hi> to serve the <hi>dotage</hi> of their <hi>superstitious</hi> Confidents.</p>
            <p>But if it be not a breach of the <hi>holy commandment</hi> thus to <hi>set up</hi> and <hi>worship</hi> their own <hi>Imaginations,</hi> (as that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned <note n="*" place="margin">B. <hi>Andr.</hi> Sermon on Acts 2. 42.</note> Bishop long ago observed) I know not what the Commandment signifies. For the <hi>command</hi> requires as
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:106773:12"/> well the <hi>affection</hi> of the <hi>spirit</hi> as the <hi>understanding</hi> of the <note place="margin">1 Cor. 14. 14, 15.</note>
               <hi>mind</hi> in prayer: but as the <hi>Romanists,</hi> by setting their people to pray they wote not what, make <hi>their under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing unfruitful,</hi> contrary to the Scripture; so <hi>these</hi>
               <note place="margin">See Pulpit. Concepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons Popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Decep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, p. 3. 9, &amp;c.</note> men, by giving themselves to <hi>imagine</hi> prayer at the same instant, they do so occupy their mind with <hi>devising what to say next,</hi> that their <hi>spirit is unfruitful,</hi> contrary to the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry same Scripture; as that reverend and learned <hi>Prelate</hi> more at large expresseth it.</p>
            <p>But seeing it is the use of their <hi>Invention</hi> that Mr. <hi>Crof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> and <hi>R. S.</hi> so earnestly plead for, I hope for the future they will lay aside their pretension of <hi>praying by the Spirit;</hi> and consequently silence those old complaints, That the <hi>Spirit is stinted</hi> by an <hi>imposed Liturgy:</hi> for we see by this Confession (extorted by the power of Truth) that it is nothing else but the <hi>stinting</hi> of their <hi>Invention.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But 3. if <hi>the formal act</hi> of the <hi>Ministerial office</hi> be the <hi>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dification</hi> of the duty by <hi>personal abilities,</hi> (i. e.) by the <hi>wit</hi> and <hi>invention</hi> of the Minister; then the <hi>Prophets</hi> and <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles</hi> failed in the very <hi>formal act</hi> of their <hi>Ministerial office</hi> in Gods service; they did not perform it by <hi>such</hi> personal abilities, for <hi>holy men of God spake</hi> (not after their own <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions,</hi> but) <hi>as they were moved by the Holy Ghost.</hi> And <note place="margin">2 Pet. 1. <hi>ult.</hi>
               </note> as to <hi>the formal act of Ministration,</hi> what difference is there betwixt a <hi>Form immediately inspired</hi> of the Holy Ghost, and one <hi>prepared</hi> by the <hi>study</hi> and <hi>prudence</hi> of our Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours, whom God hath set over us? I say, as to the <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal act of Ministration;</hi> for the <hi>worship</hi> or <hi>service</hi> of God ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ministred in <hi>these</hi> cases, is no more <hi>modified by personal abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities</hi> in the <hi>one</hi> than in the <hi>other.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>4. Again, you confess <hi>[the formal act of the Ministerial</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 4.</note>
               <hi>office is to minister]</hi> but then you adde <hi>[quomodo?</hi> is the question] and so you run from the <hi>quid sit?</hi> to the <hi>quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modo sit?</hi> which is no <hi>regular</hi> way of arguing. For, as the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:106773:13"/> Doctor said truly, to make <hi>the modification</hi> of the <hi>act</hi> the <hi>act</hi> it self, is as much as to make the <hi>apparel</hi> the <hi>man.</hi> This absurdity you endeavour to evade by saying <hi>[modification of Ministration</hi> came not into the question; but that <hi>modi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of solemn worship</hi> is <hi>the formal act of Ministration,</hi> was and is asserted.] But then if this be the definition of <hi>the formal act of Ministration,</hi> what is the <hi>genus</hi> of it? The single term <hi>[modification]</hi> cannot be it; for that hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference (as you confess) <note n="*" place="margin">A Word and a Blow, pag. 17, 18.</note> to the adjunct qualities; <hi>[gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity of expression, fervency of affection, and reverence in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meanour]</hi> yea unto those rude methods, indigested raw expressions, tautologies, solecisms and disorders, which a Minister may utter in his prayers, as Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> confes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth: and such <hi>modification of the act</hi> cannot be the <hi>genus</hi> of it. You must therefore adde some other word to it to make it serviceable to you instead of a <hi>genus;</hi> and what must that be but those terms <hi>[of solemn worship?]</hi> so that <hi>[modification of solemn worship]</hi> is your <hi>genus;</hi> and if so, then the Doctor will demand what is the <hi>specifical difference</hi> that doth distinguish the <hi>Ministration</hi> you undertake to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fine from <hi>Ministration in the general?</hi> You have nothing left but your <hi>personal abilities;</hi> and consequently the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence in this your so much magnified Definition <hi>(of the formal act of Ministration)</hi> doth not distinguish your <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stration in Gods solemn worship</hi> from your <hi>holding the stirrup</hi> to the Lord <hi>Bishop,</hi> or the <hi>candle</hi> to the <hi>Archdeacon,</hi> or the Tailors shaping his apparel; for these are all performed by <hi>personal abilities.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And therefore I cannot grant that <hi>the modification of publick worship by personal abilities is the formal act of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisterial office:</hi> it is Mr. <hi>Croftons</hi> duty, and the duty of his Advocate to prove it, (and till that be done, their Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is invalid) for <hi>Affirmanti incumbit probatio.</hi> But, to return <hi>R. S.</hi> his own words, we must believe it on the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:106773:13"/> magisterial confident <hi>say so</hi> of this <hi>great Dictator.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And because I see this is made their last <hi>refuge,</hi> which they flee to as a <hi>sanctuary</hi> to shelter them from the <hi>imposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of the <hi>Liturgy,</hi> I shall take a little more pains to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>molish it, by proving the Proposition it self to be <hi>impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable</hi> and <hi>absurd, false</hi> and <hi>scandalous;</hi> which I shall endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour by these Arguments.</p>
            <p>1. That Opinion that hath no ground in <hi>Scripture, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity</hi> or <hi>Reason,</hi> is improbable.</p>
            <p>This Opinion, That <hi>modification</hi> of publick worship by personal abilities is the <hi>formal act</hi> of the <hi>Ministerial office</hi> hath no ground in <hi>Scripture, Antiquity</hi> or <hi>Reason.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore this Opinion, That <hi>modification</hi> of publick worship by personal abilities is the <hi>formal act</hi> of the <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterial office,</hi> is <hi>improbable.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. This Opinion hath no ground in <hi>Scripture;</hi> for there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the use of Forms of <hi>prayer, praise</hi> and <hi>benediction,</hi> is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribed to such as are <hi>engaged</hi> in the <hi>Ministerial office;</hi> and sure the Holy Ghost in Scripture would prescribe nothing destructive to <hi>the formal act</hi> of that Office.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It hath no ground in <hi>Antiquity;</hi> for there we find the use of <hi>Forms</hi> and a <hi>Liturgy</hi> composed and prescribed from time to time. <q>[An Order and regular Method of Praying, Reading the Scriptures, and Administration of other parts of Worship, in convenient time and order, successively each after other in their proper place: This Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Position, pag. 1.</note> confesses to have been used <hi>in all Churches</hi> of <hi>Jews</hi> or <hi>Christians.]</hi>
               </q> But let him shew that there was ever such a <hi>method</hi> and <hi>order</hi> without the very <hi>modifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> and <hi>form</hi> it self, till the late <hi>Directory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. This Opinion hath no ground in <hi>Reason;</hi> for to the clearest light of <hi>Reason</hi> it appears to be 1. <hi>absurd,</hi> 2. <hi>false,</hi> and 3. <hi>scandalous;</hi> and it is evinced to be so by these fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Arguments.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:106773:14"/> 1. <hi>Absurd,</hi> which is proved thus:</p>
            <p>That Opinion that placeth devotion and the <hi>solemn worship</hi> of God in prayer chiefly in the exercise of the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention,</hi> is <hi>absurd.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Opinion, that <hi>the modification of publick worship by personal abilities</hi> is <hi>the formal act</hi> of the <hi>Ministerial office,</hi> placeth devotion and the solemn worship of God in prayer chiefly in the exercise of the <hi>Invention.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore this Opinion, that <hi>the modification of publick worship by personal abilities</hi> is <hi>the formal act of the Ministerial office,</hi> is absurd.</p>
            <p>The <hi>major</hi> cannot reasonably be denied, and the <hi>minor</hi> is confessed by <hi>R. S.</hi> and Mr. <hi>Crofton, (ut supra.)</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. This Opinion is <hi>false</hi> and <hi>scandalous,</hi> which appears thus:</p>
            <p>That Opinion that makes the use of the <hi>Lords prayer,</hi> or of any <hi>Psalm</hi> of <hi>David,</hi> as a <hi>Form, destructive</hi> to, or <hi>incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistent</hi> with, the <hi>formal act</hi> of the <hi>Ministerial office,</hi> is <hi>false</hi> and <hi>scandalous.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Opinion, that <hi>modification</hi> of publick worship by <hi>personal abilities</hi> is the <hi>formal act</hi> of the <hi>Ministerial office,</hi> makes the use of the <hi>Lords prayer,</hi> or of any <hi>Psalms</hi> of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> as a <hi>Form, destructive</hi> to, or <hi>inconsistent</hi> with, the <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal act</hi> of the <hi>Ministerial office.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore this Opinion, that the <hi>modification</hi> of publick worship by personal abilities is the <hi>formal act</hi> of the <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterial office,</hi> is <hi>false</hi> and <hi>scandalous.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>These Propositions are both so evident, they need no further confirmation.</p>
            <p>I shall adde but one Argument more against this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, which is this;</p>
            <p>That which is inevitably prejudicial to the people, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by involving them in the <hi>guilt</hi> of all that <hi>non-sense</hi> and <hi>indiscretion, sedition</hi> and <hi>blasphemy,</hi> which the Minister many
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:106773:14"/> times runs into in his <hi>conceived</hi> prayers, or by interrupting and disturbing them in the performance of Gods publick worship, that is not the <hi>formal act</hi> of the <hi>Ministerial office.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the <hi>modification</hi> of publick worship by <hi>personal</hi> abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities is inevitably prejudicial to the people, either by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volving them in the <hi>guilt</hi> of all that <hi>non-sense</hi> and <hi>indiscre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, sedition</hi> and <hi>blasphemy,</hi> which the Minister many times runs into in his <hi>conceived</hi> prayers, or by interrupting and disturbing them in the performance of Gods publick worship.</p>
            <p>Therefore the <hi>modification</hi> of publick worship by <hi>perso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal</hi> abilities is not the <hi>formal act</hi> of the <hi>Ministerial office.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>major</hi> cannot be denied without <hi>scandal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>minor</hi> is evident; for either the people do not <hi>joyn</hi> in the <hi>Forms</hi> of publick worship, where <hi>non-sense</hi> and <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>discretion, sedition</hi> and <hi>blasphemy</hi> are uttered; and then (if they do not <hi>take the name of God in vain)</hi> they are at least interrupted and disturbed in the performance of Gods publick worship. Or else they do <hi>joyn</hi> in it, and then <hi>(if the people love to have it so)</hi> they are involved in <note place="margin">Jer 5. <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>1.</note> the <hi>guilt</hi> of all that <hi>non-sense</hi> and <hi>indiscretion, sedition</hi> and <hi>blasphemy,</hi> which the Minister many times runs into in his <hi>conceived</hi> prayers. This <hi>R. S.</hi> took notice of when he wrote <hi>Jerubbaal justified,</hi> and therefore he saith, <hi>[If the</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 17, 18.</note>
               <hi>people have a</hi> publick judgment <hi>of the ministerial mode of Gods worship, we are under a necessity of having what we so much complain against, and cast off,</hi> (viz.) a fixed Liturgy; <hi>for the mode of Prayer, Preaching, ministration of Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, must then be known to the people, and judged by them free from all defect and disorder, before the people can attend Gods worship in that ministration.]</hi> And a little after, <hi>[No serious sober Christian can think the people to be guilty of those</hi> rude methods; indigested raw expressions, tautologies, solecisms and disorders, <hi>which a Minister may utter in his
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:106773:15"/> Preaching and Praying; yet this is inevitable,</hi> (saith <hi>R. S.) if the people have a publick judgment by special office of the Ministerial mode of Gods worship.]</hi> But it is not the peoples want of a <hi>publick judgment by special office</hi> that will keep them from the guilt; their <hi>judgment of discretion,</hi> if they <hi>consent</hi> to it, will certainly make them <hi>guilty;</hi> and if they <hi>consent not,</hi> (when they come with a hearty devotion, find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that they cannot do it conscientiously) they are then interrupted and distracted in their duty, the performance of Gods publick worship; they cannot perform it with such persuasion of faith, such intention of mind, such fervency of affection, as they may do by a <hi>composed Form,</hi> which they know and are well <hi>assured</hi> of aforehand.</p>
            <p>But (if <hi>modification by personal abilities)</hi> if <hi>that</hi> be not it, (to save himself a labour, which he knows he is not able to accomplish) he calls upon his <hi>Antagonist</hi> to assign what is <hi>the formal act</hi> of the Gospel <hi>ministerial office,</hi> what will <hi>specifically</hi> difference it from <hi>Ministration</hi> in the <hi>general;</hi> and if it may contribute to his satisfaction, I shall readily obey his command, and tell him from the Holy Ghost in Scripture that it is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. If you will have it <note place="margin">Acts 13. 2.</note> more fully, it is <hi>The Ministration of a person duly admitted into holy Orders</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Heb. 5 4.</note>, <hi>performed to the glory of God</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Acts 13. 2.</note>
               <hi>and the benefit of his Church</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Heb. 5. 1.</note>, <hi>by a Form prescribed ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">To this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce inspiration.</note>
               <hi>immediately</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Num. 6. 23. Luke 11. 2.</note>
               <hi>by God himself, or by such as are clothed with</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">See Pulpit-Concepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, pag. 56, 57, 58, 59, 60.</note>
               <hi>Authority, according to the word of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now having not onely <hi>shaken</hi> the Tree, but <hi>grubb'd up</hi> (that which is acknowledged to be) the very <hi>root</hi> of Mr. <hi>Croftons</hi> Argumentation, the most difficult part of my task is dispatched.</p>
            <p>But <hi>R. S.</hi> renews Mr. <hi>Croftons</hi> Objection in these words, <hi>[Imposition and Prescription in Prayer and Sacraments is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicable to Preaching.]</hi> To this the Doctor shaped a four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:106773:15"/> Answer, and we must consider what <hi>R. S.</hi> hath replied to it. The Doctor saith,</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>A Sermon is never the worse for being well digested.]</hi> To this <hi>R. S.</hi> replies, <hi>[True, if it be the Preachers own medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, much the better.]</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Saith the Doctor, <hi>If it be seen and allowed by Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, I know no harm in it.]</hi> R. S. replies, <hi>Nor I neither; but this is not necessary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Saith the Doctor, <hi>This course (if not endless) would more secure the peace and solid Edification of the Church.]</hi> Here <hi>R. S.</hi> begins to be transported, as if the Doctor had touch'd his <hi>Copy-hold,</hi> and falls foul upon <hi>that,</hi> which even now he confessed he knew <hi>no harm in.</hi> For when the Doctor affirms, that if Sermons were <hi>seen and allowed by Authority,</hi> this course (if not endless) would the more <hi>secure the peace and Edification</hi> of the Church;] <hi>R. S.</hi> replies with some bitterness, <hi>[I deny that, unless by the Popish guard, Ignorance is the Mother of Devotion.]</hi> But see how <hi>prejudice</hi> and <hi>passion</hi> have <hi>eclipsed</hi> his Reason; for what is there in the <hi>countenance of Authority</hi> to cherish <hi>Ignorance?</hi> Is not the <hi>Eye</hi> of a prudent Governour matter of <hi>incitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> and his <hi>approbation</hi> matter of <hi>encouragement?</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequently then they must needs conduce to the advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Knowledge</hi> not of <hi>Ignorance.</hi> But <hi>R. S.</hi> (you must know) is a very <hi>able Scholar,</hi> and if need be, to affront his Adversary, he can bring in <hi>Proverbs</hi> by <hi>head and shoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders;</hi> and thus, having got a considerable interest in the <hi>Popish guard,</hi> he doth <hi>press</hi> and <hi>muster</hi> some of <hi>their</hi> Forces for his own service, and this amongst the rest <hi>[Ignorance is the Mother of Devotion.]</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And is not this the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> as well as the <hi>Popish guard?</hi> What think you of Mr. <hi>Case,</hi> who calling upon <note place="margin">See the Doctors <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> p. 85. <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0.</note> his Auditors to pursue <hi>Rebellion</hi> in hopes of finding out a <hi>Reformation,</hi> he tells them, they must, after the example of
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:106773:16"/>
               <hi>Abraham,</hi> go at great <hi>uncertainties</hi> (and) <hi>they knew not whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi> He thought they might possibly meet with as good fortune in following <hi>Hugh Peter's Asses,</hi> as <hi>Saul</hi> did in seek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his Father's.</p>
            <p>
               <q>But Sir (saith the <hi>Replicant)</hi> what are these to a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon not <hi>studied,</hi> much less <hi>digested</hi> by the Preacher?</q>
               <hi>[As little I confess, as this is to the Controversie in hand; but you adde]</hi>
               <q>not <hi>communicated</hi> to, <hi>but composed by</hi> pretenders to Authority? <hi>making Ministers to have no work to do,</hi> qua <hi>Ministers, but to</hi> read <hi>what they have</hi> writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, <hi>which is the Nature and Form of</hi> Homilies, <hi>and these</hi> exclusively imposed, <hi>which may as well be admitted as the Liturgy.]</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>To this I answer. 1. That <hi>R. S.</hi> his calling the <hi>Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours</hi> of the Church <hi>pretenders to Authority,</hi> is highly <hi>Schis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matical</hi> and <hi>Seditious,</hi> and smells rank of the <hi>second</hi> Article of the <hi>Solemn League and Covenant.</hi> 2. That <hi>Homilies</hi> are composed to take men off from their <hi>study</hi> and <hi>dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence,</hi> who are <hi>apt to teach</hi> in their own <hi>personal capacity,</hi> is very false; and that such Homilies are or will be <hi>exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sively imposed,</hi> is <hi>maliciously</hi> or <hi>scandalously</hi> suggested. 3. That Sermons <hi>exclusively imposed</hi> may as well be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted as the <hi>Liturgy</hi> is false, and nothing is offer'd in proof of it.</p>
            <p>But the Doctor answered, 4. That when the <hi>Presbyteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> preach other mens <hi>printed</hi> Sermons, this is no <hi>prejudice</hi> to the <hi>interest</hi> of those Sculs that hear them.] To this <hi>R. S.</hi> replies, <q>
                  <hi>[Name any such who do so,</hi> (preach other mens printed Sermons) <hi>let them bear their blame; I know no</hi> Presbyterians <hi>who so do:</hi> But if you Sir please to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire in the Parish of <hi>Christs-Church,</hi> or <hi>Martins-Ludgate London,</hi> or <hi>Henly</hi> in <hi>Sussex,</hi> you may hear of <hi>Sons</hi> of the Church who stuck not to preach Mr. <hi>Croftons</hi> own <hi>prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted</hi> Sermons: But these are preparing for <hi>Homily-mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strations.]</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:106773:16"/>
            <p> In good time: But 1. If the persons you insinuate to be guilty of this <hi>Plagiarism,</hi> did <hi>modifie</hi> his Sermons hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>somely by their own <hi>personal abilities,</hi> (in the delivery of them) Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> was beholden to them for being his <hi>Rehearsers;</hi> and their <hi>Memory</hi> is no less to be admired than his <hi>Invention.</hi> But 2. Did they preach his Sermons <hi>Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batim?</hi> If they made no use of their <hi>judgment</hi> to avoid the <hi>Sedition</hi> (usual in <hi>his</hi> discourses) assure your self <hi>they</hi> were no right <hi>Sons</hi> of the Church of <hi>England.</hi> 3. This might be a prudent design in them to <hi>try</hi> the judgment of their <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditors,</hi> whether it were the <hi>Doctrine</hi> or the <hi>Person</hi> they had in admiration: For we find many times it is not so much the <hi>matter</hi> as the <hi>gestures</hi> of the Preacher, with his <hi>tone,</hi> and the <hi>Emphasis</hi> of his words that makes the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pression upon a <hi>soft-headed-people;</hi> And there is no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter way to <hi>shame</hi> them out of their <hi>Fanaticism,</hi> than to <hi>convince</hi> them (by such instances) that they do <hi>slight</hi> or <hi>reverence</hi> the very <hi>same</hi> Doctrine, (and therefore not out of <hi>judgment,</hi> but) according to the <hi>opinion</hi> they have of the <hi>Person</hi> that doth deliver it.</p>
            <p n="4">4. I demand of <hi>R. S.</hi> whether <hi>those</hi> Sermons had the <hi>same effect</hi> upon the Hearers, when preached by those <hi>Plagiaries,</hi> which they had when they were preached by Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> himself? If they had, then there is as much <hi>vertue</hi> towards <hi>Salvation</hi> in a discourse <hi>framed</hi> to my hand, as is in those of my own <hi>composition;</hi> and consequently the fault is not in the <hi>thing</hi> it self, but only in the <hi>Laziness</hi> of the Man that has <hi>personal abilities</hi> and neglecteth to <hi>exert</hi> them for the Service of the Church; if they had not <hi>the same vertue,</hi> then the <hi>efficacy</hi> of the <hi>Ministry</hi> is <hi>ex opere operantis,</hi> from the <hi>intention</hi> and <hi>quality</hi> of the <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster;</hi> and so <hi>R. S.</hi> falls in to the <hi>Popish guard</hi> again. Last<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, we must take notice, that in vilifying <hi>Homily-ministra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> (as he calls them) he puts contempt (in effect) upon
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:106773:17"/> the <hi>Reading of the Holy Scriptures.</hi> But <hi>this</hi> the <hi>Holy Ghost</hi> accounts a kind of preaching; <hi>For</hi> Moses <hi>in old time hath in every City them that preach him, being read in the Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogues</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 15. 21.</note>
               <hi>every Sabbath day.</hi> These <hi>Preachments</hi> we are sure are nothing <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> but <hi>the Word of God;</hi> but <hi>those other,</hi> though the <hi>Ordinance</hi> of God, yet are they subject to more <hi>perversities,</hi> and many times men give so much way to their own <hi>passions</hi> and <hi>conceits</hi> in <hi>them,</hi> that they are no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing less than that pure word.</p>
            <p>But to proceed, <hi>[you think</hi> (saith <hi>R. S.) there is</hi> a vast difference between Praying and Preaching; <hi>is there not also a difference between these and Sacraments?]</hi> Yes, but what then? make your inference and we shall find you an answer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>R. S</hi> goes on, and bids the Doctor <q>
                  <hi>[prove that</hi> Christ taught that Prayer may be comprised in a short Office: <hi>He suggested</hi> matter, <hi>did he determine the</hi> mode, terms, words, and expressions of Prayer? <hi>If not, what avails this Plea?]</hi>
               </q> So <hi>R. S.</hi> disputeth.</p>
            <p>But what need this <hi>Replicant</hi> bid the Doctor prove <hi>that Christ taught that prayer may be comprised in a short Office?</hi> Hath he not taught this by an example? Sure, when he gratified the <hi>piety</hi> of his <hi>Disciples</hi> inquiry after instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in this point, he did not <hi>for a pattern,</hi> what the <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rises</hi> did <hi>for a pretence</hi> when they <hi>devour'd widows houses;</hi> he did not make <hi>a long prayer.</hi> No, if we may believe Mr. <hi>Croftons</hi> Advocate, the Church of God hath been mistaken more than 1600. years: For, saith he, Christ suggested <hi>Matter,</hi> (but) did he determine the <hi>mode, terms, words, and expressions of Prayer?</hi> If not, saith he, <hi>what a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vails this plea?]</hi> You say right Sir, but in good earnest are you grown so great a <hi>proficient</hi> in <hi>Reformation,</hi> that you have forgotten your <hi>Pater-Noster?</hi> Or, how came you by that <hi>notion</hi> (so long concealed from all the blessed
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:106773:17"/>
               <hi>Saints</hi> and <hi>Martyrs</hi> of <hi>Jesus Christ)</hi> that the <hi>Lords-Prayer</hi> signifies no more than (the <hi>Title</hi> of <hi>Pater-Noster-Row</hi> in <hi>London)</hi> a direction where you may take up <hi>Stuffs</hi> of all <hi>sorts,</hi> as you have occasion? Can you understand <hi>common sense?</hi> What is the meaning of <hi>[when ye pray say,</hi> [OUR FATHER WHICH ART IN HEAVEN, &amp;c?] Did not our Saviour herein direct them to <hi>a Form?</hi> Did he not determine the <hi>mode, terms, words, and expressions of Prayer?</hi> If he did not (in that <hi>instance)</hi> for my part, I shall despair of ever understanding any single Sentence of the Holy Gospel.</p>
            <p>But (saith <hi>R. S.)</hi> there are not more <hi>various Texts</hi> in the Bible, than <hi>wants</hi> in the Church, and <hi>both are the</hi> Scene <hi>for variety of gifts to exercise upon.]</hi> How? not more <hi>va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Texts</hi> than <hi>wants?</hi> have you computed their num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber? Are there not at least a <hi>Million</hi> of such <hi>Texts?</hi> Are there not some thousands in one Book of Holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture? If the <hi>wants</hi> of the Church be so <hi>many,</hi> (I demand of this <hi>Replicant)</hi> must all these wants be <hi>particularly</hi> enu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merated in our <hi>Form</hi> of Prayer, or no? If they must, that <hi>Form</hi> of prayer (that contains an enumeration of so many particulars) cannot be much shorter than the whole <hi>Bible;</hi> and so long a <hi>Form</hi> is never fit for use, but in the <hi>Quadra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gesimal</hi> Fasts: I such a <hi>particular</hi> enumeration be not ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary (which indeed <hi>R. S.</hi> makes impossible)ble) but the wants of the Church may be recommended to God in <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral;</hi> then why not in a <hi>prescrib'd Liturgy?</hi> For Gods part, being the <hi>Ancient of days,</hi> and knowing our thoughts <hi>long before,</hi> he can no more be taken with the <hi>novelty</hi> than with the <hi>elegancy</hi> of our expressions. And for man, that <hi>variety</hi> of <hi>Conceptions</hi> (so earnestly contended for) hath more of <hi>temptation</hi> and <hi>peril,</hi> but not more of <hi>real</hi> advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, than a <hi>prescrib'd Liturgy,</hi> as the Doctor hath suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently evinced in other Papers <note n="*" place="margin">Pulpit-Concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</note>. Prayers are intended for
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:106773:18"/> an exercise of <hi>Devotion,</hi> not of <hi>Wit;</hi> not to <hi>inform</hi> our Maker, but to perform a <hi>duty</hi> of Solemn Worship that we may move him to be gracious. [The Title of the 102. <hi>Psal.</hi> is <hi>[A prayer for the afflicted when he is overwhelmed, and poureth out his complaint before the Lord.]</hi> Is this <hi>Psalm</hi> ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally <hi>suitable</hi> to the <hi>state</hi> of the <hi>afflicted,</hi> and fit to exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cise <hi>his</hi> Devotions? if it be, then there is no need of such an enumeration of particular <hi>wants</hi> as you speak of; if it be not, in saying so, you blame the <hi>Holy Ghost</hi> for <hi>inspiring</hi> such a <hi>Form</hi> for the use of <hi>the afflicted</hi> as is not <hi>suitable</hi> to the <hi>variety</hi> of <hi>Subjects</hi> and <hi>Conditions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>But Sir, (saith <hi>R. S.)</hi> your next makes work for the <hi>Terrae filius,]</hi> And why so?</q> The Doctor told Mr. <hi>Crof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton [His instance of the Parish Clerk and people, was neither to our prejudice nor to his purpose; for they are a general part of the holy Priesthood St.</hi> Peter <hi>speaketh of, and it is their du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to bear a part in Gods solemn Worship.]</hi> Here <hi>R. S.</hi> cries out <hi>[well level'd</hi> Doctor, <hi>I hope we shall no more hear of</hi> Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy <hi>distinct</hi> from Laity: <hi>The Parish Clerk and people are part of the Holy Priesthood;</hi> very true, (saith <hi>R. S.) [They ought to bear a part in Gods Solemn Worship;</hi> undoubtedly true (saith he:) <hi>But must that part be Ministration? Such Ministration as is the formal act of Gospel-ministry?]</hi> No, the Doctor never said it was; and therefore <hi>R. S.</hi> might have spared his <hi>out-cry</hi> in these words, <hi>[and if so, farwel holy Orders, yea, solemn Ordination to the Ministry; a man may make himself a Priest: Enter Independency, the</hi> Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deacon <hi>hath opened the door.</hi> All the Lords people are ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>the</hi> holy Priesthood; <hi>Ergo may Minister in the Ministers Office.]</hi> Thus <hi>R. S.</hi> suffers his <hi>tongue</hi> and <hi>pen</hi> to run <hi>riot</hi> for lack of the words of <hi>truth and soberness to</hi> stop them.</p>
            <p>But, saith <hi>R. S.</hi> to the Doctor, <hi>either</hi> (you say) <hi>so,</hi> [that the <hi>Part</hi> the <hi>Parish-Clerk</hi> and the <hi>People</hi> bear in Gods Solemn Worship is <hi>Ministration]</hi> or, <hi>you have said no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing]</hi>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:106773:18"/> yes, altogether as much as he had need to say up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that account.</p>
            <p>The Doctor did distinguish <hi>the Ministerial Office</hi> and <hi>the Ministerial Act</hi> as well as Mr. <hi>Crofton;</hi> and had you not shut your eyes on purpose, you must have seen it; for he told you, <hi>we must not so look to</hi> personal abilities <hi>as to forget</hi>
               <note place="margin">Antidote p. 110.</note> Divine Ordination.</p>
            <p>If Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> does not allow <hi>personal abilities</hi> to confer an <hi>Office,</hi> what does he infer from the abilities of the <hi>Boy</hi> to <hi>read,</hi> and the <hi>Parish Clerk</hi> to say <hi>Amen?</hi> That the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of a <hi>Gospel-minister</hi> imports a <hi>greater work</hi> than what is <hi>performable</hi> by <hi>ordinary</hi> people, the Doctor doth allow you; and he hath told you what that work is, in his <hi>Pulpit-Conceptions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You may boast what you please of your <hi>Reply,</hi> but for all <hi>this</hi> (your Vindication) Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> appears still to be <hi>self-condemned;</hi> And what ever your <hi>Jury</hi> of <hi>freshmen</hi> do by the Doctors <hi>Logick,</hi> I am sure a <hi>Jury</hi> of good <hi>Casuists</hi> will condemn your <hi>Divinity:</hi> And yet whoever has your <hi>Vote</hi> for the Office of <hi>Senior Lecturer,</hi> such is the <hi>height</hi> of your <hi>insolence,</hi> you will keep the <hi>scorners Chair</hi> to your self.</p>
            <p>But I am weary of <hi>R. S.</hi> his <hi>vanity,</hi> and therefore I shall proceed presently to make good the Doctors under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking, <hi>viz.</hi> That Mr. <hi>Crofton and his party</hi> are bound <hi>to submit to the use of a prescrib'd Liturgy.]</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This the Doctor proves (by this <hi>Medium)</hi> because it is <hi>morally possible;</hi> And this he proves (by this <hi>Medium)</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause <hi>it is not sinful;</hi> And this he makes good (by this <hi>Medium)</hi> because <hi>it is forbiddden by no Law.]</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And here we are to joyn issue. For <hi>R. S.</hi> denies <hi>This,</hi> (which was the <hi>major</hi> Proposition of the Doctors <hi>syllo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gism)</hi> and saith, that <hi>to submit to the use of a prescrib'd Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>First Commadement,</hi> which doth
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:106773:19"/> require <hi>faithfulness</hi> in the <hi>Office</hi> committed to us by the Lord himself; <hi>Ministers of God</hi> cannot without sin become the <hi>Ministers of men.]</hi> Thus disputes the <hi>Replicant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But what! <hi>To submit to the use of a prescrib'd Liturgy</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden in the <hi>First Commandement?</hi> Some men have an art to infer <hi>Quidlibet ex quolibet,</hi> like the man that could <note place="margin">Parker.</note> find the <hi>sign of the Cross</hi> to be a sin against every one of the <hi>ten</hi> Commandements. [The <hi>First Commandement</hi> is this, <hi>[Thou shalt have no other Gods before me.</hi> This <hi>Repli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant</hi> infers, <hi>Ergo, Thou shalt not submit to the use of a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scrib'd Liturgy.]</hi> Is this good <hi>Logick?</hi> Just such Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments we find in the Church of <hi>Rome; Rogavi pro te</hi> (Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre) <hi>ne deficeret fides tua,</hi> and again, <hi>Pasce oves meas;</hi> Ergo, <hi>Papa est Judex Controversiarum.</hi> Truly, in such <hi>Inferences</hi> as these the <hi>Consequences</hi> are so <hi>remote</hi> there is need of more than an <hi>ordinary sagacity,</hi> (such as that of <hi>R. S.)</hi> to discern them. What you object against the Doctor is now very applicable to your self, <hi>Dolosus versatur in generalibus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But suppose the Doctor should put you in mind of the <hi>First Commandement,</hi> and tell you, that by the <hi>duty</hi> you owe unto Almighty God (required in <hi>that</hi> Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) you are obliged <hi>to submit to the use of a prescrib'd Liturgy;</hi> would not his <hi>consequence</hi> be as <hi>rational</hi> as yours? If this <hi>Deduction</hi> be <hi>remote</hi> and <hi>doubtful,</hi> so is yours too; and whose judgment shall we relie upon in this case? You cannot be so <hi>irrational</hi> (if you be a man) as to think we ought to relie on <hi>yours,</hi> because you are a <hi>Party;</hi> and you will plead that the Doctor is so too, and consequently it is no less <hi>unreasonable</hi> that you should relie on his; and what will follow from hence but a necessity of our <hi>reliance</hi> (for <hi>peace</hi> and <hi>order</hi> sake) upon the <hi>Authority</hi> of the Church, as well in opposition to the <hi>Schismatical Inferencer</hi> as to the <note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Prid.</hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>. fol <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>)</hi> p. 391.</note>
               <hi>Fanatick Enthusiast?</hi> Thus that Learned <hi>Professor</hi> in his Lecture <hi>(De Authoritate Ecclesiae in rebus Fidei)</hi> hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined:
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:106773:19"/> For, he observes, <hi>ut de</hi> illuminatione Spiritus <hi>in litibus definiendis, potest esse</hi> dissensus, <hi>quia unusquis{que}</hi> Fanaticus <hi>jactabit</hi> suum Spiritum: <hi>Ita etiam in</hi> Conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quentiis deducendis <hi>ex</hi> indubitatis principiis, <hi>oriatur lis de</hi> Syllogismo, <hi>an secundùm</hi> rectam rationem <hi>contexatur. Quoniam quae tibi videtur</hi> recta ratiocinatio, <hi>alius</hi> pugnabit, <hi>non esse</hi> rectam, <hi>&amp; sic nunquam erit</hi> Contentionis <hi>periodus.</hi> The difference therefore must be decided by a more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent <hi>Judicature,</hi> that is, by <hi>Authority.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now I shall tell this bold <hi>Champion,</hi> that the <hi>First Commandement</hi> doth require his <hi>submission</hi> to the use of a <hi>prescrib'd Liturgy;</hi> at least the <hi>First</hi> Commandement <hi>with promise:</hi> For <hi>that</hi> Commandement saith <hi>[Honour thy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and thy Mother,] The Prince</hi> and <hi>the Church;</hi> whose duty it is to see, that (in Gods service) all things be done <hi>decent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and in order,</hi> to the <hi>Glory of God</hi> and <hi>the Edification of</hi> his people. If our <hi>Liturgy</hi> were designed to this end, (and your <hi>Superiours</hi> do tell you it was <hi>composed</hi> upon no other account) you are <hi>obliged</hi> to the <hi>Imposition,</hi> as the Doctor hath elsewhere <note n="*" place="margin">Pulpit. Concepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons p. 58, &amp;c.</note> maintain'd by <hi>irrefragable</hi> Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions.</p>
            <p>But you allege, That the <hi>First Commandement doth require Faithfulness in the Office committed to us by the Lord himself.</hi> But give me leave to as ask you a question or two. What <hi>parts</hi> of the <hi>Ministerial Office</hi> are committed to you? and <hi>how far?</hi> and by <hi>whom?</hi> Sure your Power is not <hi>unlimited,</hi> nor your Jurisdiction <hi>universal.</hi> Was the Office committed to you <hi>immediately</hi> by God himself, or <hi>mediately</hi> by the Ministry of such as have a <hi>higher</hi> Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity than your self? Did they <hi>understand</hi> the <hi>bounds</hi> of your Office when they <hi>Ordain'd</hi> you? Is not <hi>their</hi> Office <hi>committed</hi> to <hi>them</hi> by the <hi>Lord</hi> himself as well as yours? Doth not the <hi>First Commandement</hi> concern <hi>them</hi> as well as you? and requires <hi>Faithfulness</hi> in <hi>their</hi> Office too? Why,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:106773:20"/>
               <hi>they</hi> will tell you, it is out of <hi>Faithfulness</hi> to the <hi>Trust</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed in <hi>them,</hi> and to discharge <hi>their</hi> Office, that <hi>they</hi> have <hi>composed</hi> and <hi>prescrib'd</hi> such a <hi>Liturgy.</hi> Do <hi>they</hi> aver this without Reason? Was the <hi>Form</hi> (you so <hi>caulesly</hi> though <hi>furiously</hi> declaim against) <hi>imposed</hi> upon you without any <hi>previous examination</hi> or <hi>deliberate judgment?</hi> If this can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be affirmed without impudence, then I ask further; have not <hi>they</hi> Judicium Rationale &amp; Discretionis privatae, <hi>a Rational judgment of Discretion</hi> as well as you? and is not <hi>that</hi> sufficient to satisfie <hi>their</hi> Conscience, as well as <hi>yours</hi> is to satisfie your own? <hi>This</hi> then puts <hi>them</hi> upon an <hi>equal</hi> competition, and makes the <hi>scales</hi> betwixt you and them hang <hi>even.</hi> Where then is your <hi>common justice</hi> with your <hi>private judgment?</hi> Is there no <hi>allowance</hi> to be granted them upon the account of their <hi>Authority?</hi> If you be the Author of <hi>Jerubbaal justified,</hi> therein you acknowledge a <hi>judgment</hi> of <hi>office</hi> armed with a <hi>moral power</hi> which the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple have not, [pag. 17, and 18.] and (pag. 35.) you say, though the <hi>forum</hi> of the Church <hi>visible</hi> be changeable and is changed, yet it <hi>consisteth</hi> (even now) of such, who are <hi>true</hi> and <hi>lawful</hi> (though it may be not pious) <hi>Ministers of the Gospel,</hi> and <hi>these</hi> you confess <hi>are Judges:</hi> And what? must their <hi>Judicium forense &amp; Decisionis Publicae,</hi> their legal Authority and publick Decision stand for nothing? Or is it a sufficient <hi>security</hi> to your Conscience to <hi>confront</hi> your <hi>Christian liberty</hi> to their <hi>Authority?</hi> If your <hi>Creed</hi> be of the same dimensions with the <hi>Confession of Faith</hi> advi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed by the <hi>Assembly,</hi> you believe otherwise; for they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fess, <note place="margin">Chap. 20. Sect. 4.</note> That <hi>they who upon pretence of Christian Liberty shall oppose any lawful power, or the lawful exercise of it, whether it be Civil or Ecclesiastical, resist the Ordinance of God;]</hi> and then you may learn from the Apostle what will follow, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 2.</p>
            <p>But you add <hi>[Ministers of God cannot without sin become
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:106773:20"/> the Ministers of men.]</hi> How? not the Ministers of men? Had not the men of <hi>Salamis John</hi> to their <hi>Minister?</hi> Are <note place="margin">Acts 13. 5.</note> there not some men of whom the Lord himself affirms, <hi>I have said ye are Gods?</hi> You will make them <hi>sorry</hi> Gods indeed (and you are very well acquainted how your <hi>confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derates</hi> used his late Majesty) if you allow them no <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters</hi> in their utmost exigencies.</p>
            <p>But perhaps your meaning is good, though your words be liable to exception. If your <hi>sense</hi> be this, that we ought not to <hi>resign</hi> our selves up in a <hi>blind obedience</hi> to the <hi>Magisterial</hi> dictates of men, without any <hi>examination</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they be <hi>consonant</hi> to Gods word or otherwise, I do rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily <hi>subscribe</hi> to it.</p>
            <p>For (1) if there should happen to be a <hi>competition</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>them</hi> in matters <hi>clearly determined</hi> in Holy Scripture, or <hi>evidently consequential</hi> to any <hi>divine determination,</hi> it is our acknowledged duty to <hi>obey God rather than men.</hi> But this Rule ties you up more <hi>indispensably</hi> to the commands of your Superiours in all cases wherein God hath made no such exception; for <hi>[Exceptio firmat regulam in Casibus non exceptis.]</hi> If therefore you have any such exception in the Case of a <hi>prescrib'd Liturgy,</hi> produce it in Gods name; for your Governours will tell you that God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands your obedience to their injunctions; and he having invested them with Authority over you, they are by that means possest of a right to command you from God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self. In this case how can you supersede their power? If you pretend to a Divine Authority to justifie your disobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, you allege no more than what they really have to command you. And then, unless the Authority you pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to, be more evident for you, than that by which they claim their power to command you, is for them: it remains at least <hi>doubtful</hi> on which side the Right lies; whether on your Governours side who command, or on yours that
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:106773:21"/> refuse obedience; and in all <hi>doubtful Cases</hi> it is an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged Rule, <hi>Potier est pars possidentis;</hi> the <hi>presump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> is alwayes for those in Authority, else Peace and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der must expire.</p>
            <p>But besides (2) in <hi>doubtful</hi> matters, who should we have recourse unto but to such as are most versed in that facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that examins them? We should consult the <hi>Physician</hi> for our <hi>Health,</hi> and the <hi>Lawyer</hi> for our <hi>Title</hi> to an <hi>Estate;</hi> but we have all the reason in the world to trust the <hi>Divine</hi> with our <hi>Case of Conscience.</hi> The learned <hi>Davenant</hi> (as you deservedly style him) hath soberly determin'd in this particular; <hi>Pendere</hi> (Deus ipse) <hi>noluit fidem Ecclesiae suae ab</hi> absolutâ <hi>Authoritate</hi> Praedicantium: <hi>Voluit</hi> (tamen) <hi>uti Ministerio hominum in verbi salutiferi praedicatione; voluit etiam ab omnibus Christianis horum Ministrorum vocem cum debito honore atque</hi> summa <hi>reverentia audiri.</hi> Can the Learning and Piety of that Reverend <hi>Prelate</hi> prevail with you? Behold (in your Opinion perhaps) a greater than <hi>Davenant</hi> is here, we have even Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Nose-gay to Mr. <hi>Caril</hi> p. 83.</note> himself our <hi>Suffragane</hi> in this Article; he tells his <hi>Brethren</hi> of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistry, <hi>[though</hi> he <hi>denies them to have either Credit or Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority against the known</hi> word <hi>of God, yet so great is their Credit and Authority even as Teachers and Guides of the Church in Cases</hi> agreeable <hi>to the</hi> word, <hi>and in Cases to the people</hi> doubtful <hi>and</hi> unknown, <hi>and in Cases</hi> left <hi>by the word to</hi> their <hi>determination, (the word determining them but</hi> ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally) <hi>that</hi> he <hi>thinks the ignorance of</hi> this <hi>truth hath been the main Cause of our sad</hi> Confusions <hi>and</hi> Schisms <hi>in</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land; <hi>and that the</hi> Ministers <hi>have been guilty of it; and that till we have better taught even our</hi> Godly <hi>people, what Credit and Obedience is due to their</hi> Teachers <hi>and</hi> Spiritual Guides, <hi>the Church of</hi> England <hi>shall never have</hi> Peace <hi>or any</hi> good <hi>or</hi> establish'd <hi>Order,</hi> &amp;c. (as is more fully cited in the very <note place="margin">Antidote p. 105.</note> next page before [Mr. <hi>Croftons</hi> Position examined.]</p>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:106773:21"/>
            <p> 3. To keep out <hi>Faction,</hi> to prevent <hi>Confusion,</hi> and to preserve <hi>Unity,</hi> God hath been pleased to establish a <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordination</hi> of Ministers in his <hi>Church,</hi> as well under the <hi>New</hi> as under the <hi>Gld</hi> Testament <note n="*" place="margin">See Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dote p. 9. &amp;c.</note>. And as there is <hi>a judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Discretion</hi> that belongs to <hi>all,</hi> and a <hi>judgement</hi> of <hi>Direction</hi> that belongs to single <hi>Presbyters,</hi> so there is a <hi>judgment of Jurisdiction</hi> peculiar to the <hi>Prelacy.</hi> Every man for the <hi>satisfaction</hi> of his <hi>own</hi> Conscience may inquire and examine such <hi>Doctrines, Rites,</hi> and <hi>Forms</hi> of <hi>Worship</hi> as are <hi>delivered</hi> or <hi>prescribed</hi> to him; his <hi>judgement</hi> of <hi>Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion</hi> is given him to this purpose; and he will pay his <hi>submission</hi> with the more <hi>alacrity</hi> to those whom God hath set over him, when he finds their <hi>Discourses</hi> and <hi>Injuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> consonant to <hi>divine</hi> Revelations. But what if upon such their <hi>exploration</hi> it should seem as well to some of those that have a <hi>Directive judgment,</hi> as to others who have only a <hi>judgment of Discretion,</hi> that somethings are to be <hi>held</hi> or <hi>practised</hi> otherwise than their <hi>Superiours</hi> have <hi>detertermined?</hi> Why, in this Case <hi>Christianae erit modestiae diffidere potiùs</hi> privatae perspicaciae, <hi>quàm Reverendo</hi> Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latorum <note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Brid.</hi> Lect. 22.</note>
               <hi>coetui</hi> (as that Learned <hi>Professor</hi> hath resolved) <hi>it becomes their Christian modesty rather to</hi> distrust <hi>their own</hi> private <hi>in-sight</hi> (into the nature of those particulars) than the Reverend College of their Prelates, to whom be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs the judgment of Jurisdiction. And if possibly they should deprehend some <hi>manifest prevarication, non medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tandum statim</hi> schisma, <hi>sed</hi> communicandum <hi>in receptis;</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerandum <hi>quod</hi> tolli <hi>non potest, &amp;</hi> expectandum <hi>demum, &amp;</hi> orandum, <hi>donec Deus</hi> suo tempore <hi>quod</hi> distortum <hi>est aut</hi> luxatum, <hi>legitima aliquâ</hi> Authoritate <hi>ac</hi> debitis mediis, <hi>in integrum restituat.</hi> And this is not at all to become <hi>sinful,</hi> or the <hi>servants of men,</hi> but to walk <hi>worthy of the Lord</hi> unto all <hi>pleasing,</hi> and to keep the unity of the Spirit in the bond of peace, as <hi>becomes the Gospel of Christ, and Gods Ministers.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:106773:22"/>
            <p> But if the <hi>First Commandement</hi> will not justifie his <hi>Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>submission</hi> to Authority in the <hi>use</hi> of a <hi>prescrib'd Liturgy,</hi> he hath another <hi>special</hi> Law will do it; for he saith</p>
            <p>2. <hi>In specialty, the Law of the Ministerial office in its speci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al nature (which must give Rules to the Ministers acts,</hi> qua <hi>Ministerial acts) doth forbid such submission,</hi> as inconsistent with, <hi>and</hi> destructive to <hi>the formal act</hi> of the <hi>Ministerial office, viz.</hi> Modifying worship by personal abilities, <hi>not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding what our Opponent hath urged to the contrary.]</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this I answer, That <hi>the formal act of the Ministerial office</hi> is not the <hi>modifying</hi> of worship <hi>by personal abilities</hi> (as hath been proved formerly) but is <hi>consistent</hi> with and <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded</hi> in <hi>the performance of Gods Publick Worship and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice,</hi> by a <hi>Form prescrib'd,</hi> either <hi>immediately</hi> by <hi>God himself,</hi> or <hi>by the Church</hi> according to the <hi>word</hi> of God. And I do challenge <note n="*" place="margin">See Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit-Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept. p. 56, 57.</note> this <hi>Replicant</hi> to produce his <hi>special Law</hi> or <hi>prohibition</hi> to the contrary. For what he adds is not of force against us; <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That 3. <hi>The edifying of the Church by variety of Ministe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial gifts, is a Law which doth forbid such submission as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stiuctive to that end.]</hi> It seems your shift of Pasture makes fat Souls too; and then I wonder your Law doth not likewise forbid the settlement of any one single person over a <hi>particular Congregation;</hi> and injoyn all Ministers to become <hi>Itinerant,</hi> that travelling up and down their <hi>variety of gifts</hi> may be the more <hi>diffused</hi> to the <hi>edifying</hi> of the Church. But if you take the <hi>Liturgy prescrib'd</hi> in the full extent of it, it allows you room enough in the <hi>Pulpit,</hi> and upon all <hi>incidental occasions</hi> to exercise your <hi>variety</hi> of gifts amongst the people. And if you restrain it to the <hi>several Forms</hi> of <hi>Confession, Prayer,</hi> and <hi>Thanksgiving,</hi> They are designed to exercise your <hi>heart</hi> rather than your <hi>brain,</hi> and it is <hi>their</hi> proper office to <hi>edifie</hi> your <hi>Devotion</hi> not your <hi>Knowledge</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Unless it be <hi>impetra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive</hi> or <hi>d<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spositive.</hi>
               </note>. And <hi>prescrib'd Forms</hi> are of so
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:106773:22"/> much the more advantage to this effect, because the less the <hi>understanding</hi> is occupied to <hi>consider and invent</hi> the mater, the more <hi>intent</hi> and <hi>earnest</hi> are the <hi>will</hi> and <hi>affections</hi> (the most <hi>immediate instruments of Devotion)</hi> about the <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly duty</hi> it self, as hath been evinced elsewhere <note n="*" place="margin">Pulpit-Concepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons p. 39. to 45.</note>.</p>
            <p>But to follow this bold Champion; <hi>the Apostle indeed</hi> (saith he) <hi>bids us hold fast the</hi> Form of wholsome words, <hi>but not to hold to the</hi> same words; <hi>to speak the</hi> same things, <hi>but not in the</hi> same <hi>Syllables:]</hi> And why so? <hi>Chemnitius</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Harm. Evang.</hi> c. 51. p 522.</note> was of another mind touching the practice of our Saviour, and the duty of the Church: NULLUM DUBIUM <hi>est, eandem doctrinam, &amp; easdem Conciones, iisdem verbis saepius aliis at{que} aliis temporibus &amp; locis a Christo repetitas:</hi> There is no doubt but Christ did often repeat the very same Doctrine and the very same Sermons <hi>in the very same words</hi> at several times and places. <hi>Non enim valere debet in Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesia illud Rhetorum praeceptum,</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Sed illud</hi> Iraenei <hi>potiùs valere debet,</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. For that rule of the <hi>Rhetorician</hi> should not prevail in the Church of God; <hi>[the affecting to cloath common truth in a new dress:]</hi> but that of <hi>Iraeneus</hi> should prevail rather, <hi>[the delivering of the same Article in the same expressions.] To write the same</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil 3. 1.</note>
               <hi>things unto you, to me indeed is not grievous, but for you it is safe,</hi> saith the great Apostle; and words are not to be multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed <note place="margin">Entià non sunt mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplicanda sine necessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate.</note> to no purpose.</p>
            <p>But, <hi>if so,</hi> saith our Adversary, i. e. if we speak <hi>the same things</hi> in <hi>the same words,</hi> (then) <hi>the Liturgy must be</hi> Catholick <hi>to all Christians in all places and ages of the World, and that in the</hi> Greek <hi>language only.]</hi> To which I answer, 1. That if there were one <hi>Catholick language,</hi> such a <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Liturgy</hi> would be very desirable to all such as love to keep the <hi>unity</hi> of the Spirit in the bond of Peace. <hi>O quam</hi>
               <note place="margin">Psal.</note>
               <hi>bonum &amp; quam jucundum!</hi> But 2. because all the World is not of one language, and because we must pray with the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:106773:23"/>
               <hi>understanding</hi> as well as with the heart and affections; therefore the same Apostle that requireth all <hi>to speak the same thing</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">1 Cor. 1. 10.</note>, gives a warrant for <hi>interpretation,</hi> that all may be edified <note n="b" place="margin">1 Cor. 14. 14, &amp;c.</note>. 3. It is observable, that his Direction is ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dressed, as his Epistle is, to a Church of <hi>one</hi> denomination and language; to the <hi>Romans</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Rom. 15. 6.</note>, to the <hi>Corinthians</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">1 Cor. 1. 10.</note>, &amp;c. 4. The Doctor does not contend for the absolute <hi>necessity</hi> of our prescribed <hi>Liturgy,</hi> but <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nly for the <hi>lawfulness</hi> and <hi>expediency</hi> of it.</p>
            <p>But our <hi>Antagonist</hi> goes on thus, <hi>[had this Doctor</hi> read Mr. Croftons <hi>Argument on this Question against</hi> D. G. <hi>he sure would not have thus disputed.]</hi> And why so? (he adds) <hi>Submission to Superiours is a duty;]</hi> a good confessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on if it were not for the <hi>But</hi> that follows, <hi>[but our</hi> judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cium rationale <hi>must judge their Mandate to be</hi> licitum &amp; ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nestum, <hi>which in this Case we cannot do; and then our</hi> Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemma <hi>is manifest,</hi> shall we obey God or man? <hi>judge you.]</hi> But maugre this mans <hi>prejudice</hi> we have proved their <hi>Mandate</hi> in this case to be <hi>licitum &amp; honestum,</hi> and therefore to resist it is neither more nor less than to <hi>resist the Ordinance of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But you were lately told upon another occasion <note n="*" place="margin">Reply to <hi>S. C.</hi> &amp;c. p. 511.</note>, that <hi>the defence of the Apostles</hi> [we must obey God rather than man] <hi>is very unseemly in the mouths of Rebels.]</hi> Neither will the horns of that <hi>Dilemma</hi> assist you in this encounter, for to secure your Conscience and warrant your Non-sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission to your Governours, the evidence you produce to prove that it is Gods <hi>will</hi> you should not obey them in this instance, must be more <hi>clear</hi> and pregnant than those Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stimonies that are pleadable for their Authority to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand you; otherwise your Conscience if it be <hi>tender</hi> and <hi>awake</hi> to do its office, must needs be <hi>perplexed, scrupulous,</hi> and <hi>doubtful,</hi> unless you have drunk as deep of the <hi>Jesuits</hi> Cup in this Doctrine, as you have done in some others,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:106773:23"/> and perswade your self, that in your practices relating to your Superiours you may govern your self by that <hi>opinion</hi> which is less <hi>probable;</hi> which course, how unreasonable, how unsafe and dangerous it is you are apt to proclame loud enough in other instances.</p>
            <p>Your Governours command you to submit to the use of <hi>a prescribed Liturgy;</hi> you despise this command, and tell <hi>them</hi> you must <hi>obey God rather than men.</hi> Now the <hi>quaere</hi> is, who hath the fairest Title to a <hi>Divine Revelation</hi> for their justification, whether your <hi>Governours</hi> for their <hi>Command,</hi> or <hi>you</hi> for your <hi>Recusancy</hi> and disobedience?</p>
            <p>They allege the <hi>prime, literal,</hi> and <hi>immediate</hi> importance of the holy Text <hi>[Let every Soul be subject to the higher powers, obey them that have the rule over you, and submit your selves.]</hi> This is their <hi>grand Charter</hi> to command you, their <hi>general</hi> Title to require obedience from you; but where is your Charter of <hi>Exemption,</hi> your <hi>privilege</hi> that frees you from your duty in this instance? Doth the <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>persedeas</hi> your Conscience relies upon run in these (or the like) express and clear terms <hi>[Do not obey them that have the rule over you do not submit your selves in the use of a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribed Liturgy?]</hi> Had you such a <hi>Divine Revelation</hi> in the holy Text, then <hi>you</hi> had as fair a Title for your <hi>Recusancy</hi> as your <hi>Governours</hi> have for their <hi>Command.</hi> But you cannot, you dare not pretend to such a <hi>Divine Dispensation</hi> in <hi>this</hi> case. But what is the course you take? Why, turning your back upon the <hi>clear light</hi> that leads you to your duty, you betake your selves to the <hi>obscure shades,</hi> and serve your interest of any colour that you think will give a handsome <hi>appearance</hi> to your disobedience.</p>
            <p>You are injoyned the use of a prescribed <hi>Liturgy,</hi> and flying from your duty, you take Sanctuary in the <hi>First Commandement,</hi> which, in the <hi>first, literal,</hi> and <hi>immediate</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance of it, hath nothing to the purpose; and so your
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:106773:24"/> appeal is made to a <hi>Consequence,</hi> which, if at all <hi>deducible</hi> from thence, is so <hi>remote</hi> and distant, that to most mens eyes it is <hi>invisible.</hi> Thus you forsake the <hi>good</hi> and <hi>safe old way</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">In dubiis par<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> tu<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>or est eligenda. Tene certum &amp; di<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>te incertum.</note>; you let go that which is <hi>clear and certain,</hi> to follow what is <hi>obscure, doubtful, and uncertain.</hi> Do you thus ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercise your self in the Law of God? Is this your way to have <hi>a Conscience</hi> alwayes <hi>void of offence</hi> towards God and towards man?</p>
            <p>When you refuse obedience to the commands of your <hi>Superiours,</hi> you had need be very well assured of your warrant for it: The <hi>Casuists</hi> tell you, your grounds must be as clear as those upon which you are required to take a <hi>solemn Oath;</hi> for you do as much engage your Soul in one case as in the other, in both you pledge your interest in Gods favour, and venture your Salvation <note n="*" place="margin">See Rom 13. 2. Mat. 18. 17.</note>. And it is observable, that God hath been more <hi>severe</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">See <hi>Men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>za in</hi> 1. <hi>Reg. c.</hi> 3. 10. <hi>Sect.</hi> 2. <hi>Tom.</hi> 2. <hi>p. mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>i.</hi> 63.</note> in his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions toward such as have <hi>despised</hi> the commands of their <hi>Governours,</hi> than towards such as have dis-obeyed his <hi>own</hi> voice.</p>
            <p>But after all his pretensions to obey God, this <hi>Repli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant</hi> doth prevaricate the very <hi>principle</hi> he so much insists upon; for he that prefers <hi>a humane judgment</hi> before Gods <hi>express Command,</hi> doth not <hi>obey God rather than man;</hi> and thus doth he: For it is Gods express command (in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral) <hi>That we should obey them that have the Rule over us;</hi> but that we should not obey them (in this instance) <hi>in the use of a prescribed Liturgy,]</hi> is but a <hi>humane judgment;</hi> and yet he <hi>prefers</hi> and follows <hi>this</hi> judgment before <hi>that</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement.</p>
            <p>And now Sir, to return you your own words to the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor, <hi>your holding your Conclusion is not in my power to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; but if your premisses be not push'd down, let all men of Reason judge.]</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In your close, you accost the Doctor in these words
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:106773:24"/>
               <hi>[You have Sir been at the pains to transcribe Mr.</hi> Crofton's <hi>Creed</hi> in point of <hi>Church-Communion;</hi> praeterea nihil; <hi>you deny no one Article, nor Dispute not against them</hi> (if that be good English;) <hi>herein then</hi> (you say) <hi>we are agreed; only Sir, let me tell you, that</hi> freedom from corruptions and disorders <hi>must be secured to the Church by</hi> the wayes God hath di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected, <hi>not by words which men have</hi> dictated, <hi>and by their</hi> unwarranted <hi>power determined.]</hi> To this I answer in short, That the Governours of this Church have exercised no power but what God hath <hi>warranted,</hi> nor walked in any <hi>wayes</hi> but such as God hath <hi>directed,</hi> to secure our <hi>freedom from Corruptions and Disorders;</hi> And that it is your duty to <hi>submit</hi> to that Power, and <hi>follow</hi> those wayes, hath been sufficiently evidenced against you.</p>
            <p>For Mr. <hi>Croftons</hi> CREED, the Doctor had no other design upon it than to give the people notice of his judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>viz.</hi> That it is <hi>their</hi> duty to frequent the <hi>service</hi> of God administred by the <hi>publick Liturgy.</hi> But that it should be <hi>sin</hi> in <hi>them</hi> to <hi>absent</hi> themselves from <hi>such</hi> a <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship</hi> as Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> and his <hi>Party</hi> cannot without <hi>sin</hi> admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister unto them is a pretty <hi>Paradox,</hi> a device to teach men how they may <hi>neither go to Church nor be at home;</hi> frequenting that Service in <hi>Hypocrisie,</hi> which, according to your Doctrine, they cannot in <hi>Sincerity</hi> say <hi>Amen</hi> to.</p>
            <p>I shall conclude mine own and the Readers trouble, in this Argument, as that Reverend <hi>Professor</hi> (whom you had in great admiration till he came to wear a <hi>Roches)</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes his Lecture, <hi>De Authoritate Ecclesiae in rebus Fidei;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Prid.</hi> Lect. 22. fol. p. 36<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
               <hi>Disciplina</hi> optimè secundùm Dei praescriptum observatur, quando <hi>Publica privato</hi> non permittantur arbitrio, sed <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tistites</hi> praecipiunt, recipiunt subditi, non hi, pro illimita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to imperio, illi pro occaecato <hi>obsequi<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> sed tam <hi>hi,</hi> quam <hi>illi</hi> juxta praescriptum, a summo <hi>Agonotheta</hi> in Scripturis, <hi>Canonem;</hi> ut ergo <hi>iis</hi> incumbit, ut sine <hi>studio</hi> partium, bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:106773:25"/> fide <hi>deliberent</hi> priusquam aliquid decernunt: Ita <hi>illis perm<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ssum</hi> est, ut Expendant ad indubitatam <hi>amussim,</hi> quid <hi>injungitur,</hi> ut agnoscant se didicisse a <hi>Pastoribus</hi> quod antea <hi>ignorabant.</hi> Tale autem <hi>modestum</hi> in domino <hi>Examen, privatum</hi> non sapit <hi>spiritum,</hi> quo turgen quos aversamur; Sed <hi>solicitam</hi> spirituum <hi>probationem,</hi> an sunt <hi>a Deo: spiritus</hi> siquidem habeatur <hi>privatus,</hi> vel respectu <hi>personae,</hi> quae le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitimè <hi>quaerit;</hi> vel <hi>finis,</hi> ut sibi <hi>satis faciat;</hi> vel modi, cùm peculiarem sibi eligit <hi>quaerendi</hi> aut <hi>judicandi</hi> normam, aut <hi>formam,</hi> Neglectis istis quae a <hi>supremo Legislatore</hi> prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribuntur. Respectu <hi>personae</hi> aut <hi>finis,</hi> tantum abest, ut <hi>obstemus privatorum</hi> industriae, ut invitamus illos potius, ad <hi>Expendendam doctrinam nostram</hi> ad Sanctuarii <hi>stateram,</hi> ut sibi ipsis <hi>satisfaciant</hi> &amp; <hi>fidem</hi> nostram <hi>liberent;</hi> Qui vero secundùm <hi>hanc</hi> incedunt <hi>Regulam,</hi> pax sit super <hi>eos,</hi> &amp; <hi>Israe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem</hi> Dei; <hi>furiosi</hi> verò &amp; <hi>factiosi,</hi> qui privato elati aut in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flati <hi>lumine</hi> aut <hi>acumine,</hi> Ecclesiam cui subjiciuntur audire <hi>neglexerunt;</hi> sint cuivis <hi>fideli</hi> &amp; <hi>Orthodoxo</hi> sicut <hi>Ethnicus</hi> &amp; <hi>Publicanus,</hi> donec ex debita <hi>correptione</hi> aut <hi>correctione</hi> ad <hi>sobrietatem</hi> discant <hi>sapere,</hi> &amp; ad <hi>matris</hi> gremium redire. Quod efficiat <hi>pastor</hi> ille <hi>bonus,</hi> qui <hi>ovem</hi> Errantem propriis reportat <hi>humeris.</hi> Cui cum <hi>Patre</hi> &amp; <hi>Spiritu Sancto</hi> fit omnis <hi>honor, laus,</hi> &amp; <hi>gloria,</hi> in <hi>secula seculorum,</hi> Amen.</p>
            <p>Which may be thus rendred into English, For truly <hi>Discipline</hi> is best observed according to the Law and Ordinance of God, when Affairs that concern the <hi>pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick</hi> are not left to the Award and Determination of <hi>pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate</hi> persons; but <hi>Governours</hi> command and <hi>Subjects</hi> obey, not the former by an <hi>Unlimited</hi> and <hi>Absolute</hi> Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion, nor the latter by an Implicit and blind Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, but when <hi>Governours</hi> command and <hi>Subjects yield</hi> obedience according to the <hi>Rules</hi> mentioned in the <hi>Holy Scripture</hi> by the <hi>Supreme disposer</hi> and <hi>Lawgiver:</hi> As
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:106773:25"/> therefore it is the duty of those in Authority, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out partiality or <hi>inclining</hi> to any side with <hi>Equity</hi> and <hi>Integrity</hi> to deliberate, before they <hi>resolve</hi> or <hi>determine</hi> any thing: So, they that are to obey are allowed to examine and try by the <hi>Undeniable</hi> and <hi>Undoubted Rule,</hi> what is so enjoyned them, that they may <hi>confess</hi> and <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geniously acknowledge</hi> that they have been brought by the <hi>Care</hi> of their Governours to understand their duty, which <hi>before</hi> they were utterly <hi>Ignorant</hi> of; And such kind of <hi>modest</hi> search or trial by the <hi>Revealed</hi> Will of God savours not of a <hi>private spirit,</hi> with which <hi>they</hi> are <hi>puffed</hi> up, whom we impugn; but is rather a diligent trying of the spirits, whether they be of <hi>God</hi> or no: For as much as a Spirit may be accounted private, either in regard of the <hi>person</hi> that seeketh, or in respect of the End and Drift of seeking, which is to <hi>satisfie</hi> himself; or in reference to the manner of seeking, when one go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth a <hi>new</hi> way to work to enform his judgment, chu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing to himself a <hi>peculiar</hi> and <hi>singular Rule</hi> and <hi>Square</hi> to <hi>seek</hi> and <hi>judge</hi> by, <hi>omitting</hi> those Rules which for that very purpose have their Appointment from <hi>God Almighty.</hi> [In respect of the <hi>Person</hi> or <hi>End,</hi> we are so <hi>far</hi> from <hi>hindring</hi> the <hi>Industry</hi> of private persons, that we rather bid and <hi>invite</hi> them to <hi>weigh</hi> our Doctrine in the Ballance of the <hi>Sanctuary,</hi> that they may thereby satisfie themselves, and <hi>acquit</hi> our <hi>fidelity.</hi> And as many as walk according to this <hi>Rule, Peace</hi> be on them, and on the <hi>Israel</hi> of God; but they are <hi>Furious</hi> and <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctious,</hi> as far from <hi>Reason</hi> as <hi>Religion,</hi> who being lifted up with the <hi>Opinion</hi> of their own <hi>Judgment</hi> and <hi>Wisdom, neglect to hear</hi> the <hi>Church</hi> to which they <hi>owe Submission</hi> and <hi>Obedience:</hi> Let such stubborn Children to every <hi>sound</hi> Believer be as a <hi>Heathen</hi> and a <hi>Publican, till</hi> upon <hi>due reproof</hi> and <hi>correction</hi> they learn to be wise unto So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>briety,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:106773:26"/> and to return to the bosom of their <hi>tender Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther;</hi> which that <hi>good Sheepherd</hi> grant who bringeth home the <hi>straying</hi> Sheep upon his own <hi>shoulders;</hi> To whom with the <hi>Father,</hi> and <hi>blessed Spirit,</hi> be all <hi>Honour, Praise,</hi> and <hi>Glory,</hi> for Ever and Ever, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon_excerpt">
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:106773:26"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Doctor</hi> Edward Reynolds <hi>(now Lord Bishop of</hi> Norwich) <hi>in a Sermon Preached at the Second</hi> Triennial <hi>Visitation of the Right Reverend Father in God</hi> Francis <hi>Lord Bishop of</hi> Peterborough, <hi>at</hi> Daventry <hi>in</hi> Northampton-shire, <hi>July</hi> 12. 1637.</head>
            <p>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Pag. 13.</note> WHosoever by Pride, or Faction, or Schism, or Ambition, or Novel Fancies, or Arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gance, or Ignorance, or Sedition, or Popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larity, or Vain-Glory, or Envy, or Discontent, or Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>respondence, or any other Carnal reason, shall rend the Seamless Coat of Christ, and <hi>cause Divisions and Offences,</hi> I shall need load him with no other guilt than the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle doth, <hi>That he is not the Servant of Christ,</hi> Rom. 16. 17. For how can he who is without Peace or Love, serve that God who is the God of Peace, whose Name is Love, and whose Law is Love?</p>
            <p>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Pag. 10.</note> Greatly therefore doth it concern all of us in our Places and Orders to put to all our Power, Prayers, Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rests, for preserving the Unity of the Spirit in the bond of Peace, and for pursuing and promoting the Peace of <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rusalem,</hi> that in nothing we give offence to the Church of God; rather be willing to silence and smother our private judgments, to relinquish our particular Liberties <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and Interests, to question and mistrust <hi>domestica judicia</hi> (as <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as <hi>Chrysost.</hi> in <hi>Gen. Hom.</hi> 4.</note>
               <hi>Tertullian</hi> calls them) our singular Conceits and Fancies,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:106773:27"/> than to be in any such thing stiff and Peremptory against the quiet of Gods Church.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>[As conducible hereunto, he adviseth]</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">P. 33, 34.</note> Submission to the Spirits of the Prophets, and the judgments of the Godly learned; not to be stiff and inflexible in our own Conceits, nor to be Acceptors of our own persons, but to be willing to retract any Errour, and with meekness and thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness to be led into the right way by any hand. Excellent was the resolution of <hi>Job</hi> in this case, <hi>Teach me and I will hold my peace, and cause me to know wherein I have erred,</hi> Job 6. 34. In which one disposition did all men, who o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise differ, firmly agree, and were not too partially addicted to their own Fancies, nor had their judgments (which should be guided only by the truth of things) too much enthrall'd to their own W<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lls, Ends, or Passions; soon might they be brought, if not wherein they err, to change their judgments, yet at least so to allay them with Humility and Love (as St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> did his) that they should never break forth into bitterness towards their Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, or disturbance of the Church of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In all differences 'tis recommended as a most Compendious Remedy to observe]</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Pag. 32.</note> the Custom of the Churches of God. To retain that (when there is no express and evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent variation from Divine Authority) which is most con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonant to the received usage of the Ancient and pure Ages of the Church. This Rule the Apostle gives for sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressing of differences, <hi>If any seem to be Contentious, we have no such Custom, neither the Churches of God,</hi> 1 Cor. 11. 16. <hi>Inquire of the former</hi> Age saith <hi>Bildad, and prepare thy self to the search of their Fathers,</hi> Job 8. 8. <hi>Look to the old way</hi> saith the Prophet, <hi>Jer.</hi> 6. 16. <hi>It was not so from the beginning</hi> saith our Saviour, <hi>Mat.</hi> 19. 8. Onely this Rule is to be qualified with this necessary distinction, That no Ant quity hath any Authority in <hi>Matters necessary,</hi> of
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:106773:27"/> Faith, Worship, or Doctrines of Religion, to prescribe or deliver any thing, as <hi>in it self,</hi> and <hi>immediately</hi> obligatory to the Conscience, which is either <hi>Contradicted</hi> or <hi>omitted</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">For Satisfaction herein, Consult Doctor <hi>H. Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond</hi>'s Letter of Resolution. <hi>Quare</hi> 1. Of Resolving Controversies, <hi>per totum.</hi>
               </note> in the written Word, which we believe to be fully sufficient to make the man of God perfect, and throughly furnished unto every good Work, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 16, 17.</p>
            <p>But, 1. In <hi>Matters accessory of indifferency, order, decen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and inferiour Nature.</hi> 2. In Matter of <hi>Testimony</hi> to the Truths of Scripture, and for manifesting the Succession, Flourishing, and Harmony of Doctrines through all Ages of the Church, the Godly learned have justly ascribed much to the Authority and usage of the Ancient Churches. The study of the Doctrine and Rites whereof is justly called by the most Learned Primate of <hi>Ireland, A noble Study.</hi> I will conclude this particular with the words of St. <hi>Augustine,</hi> In those things, saith he, wherein the Holy Scripture hath defined nothing, <hi>Mos Populi Dei &amp; insti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuta Majorum pro lege tenenda sunt,</hi> the Custom of Gods people and appointments of our Fore-Fathers must be held for Laws.</p>
            <p>Discipline and Fatherly Government (is requisite) to keep the Stones of the Building in Order, and to reduce all unto Decency and Beauty: for as God must be served with <hi>Holiness,</hi> so it must be in the <hi>Beauty of Holiness</hi> too, and Unity is the Beauty of the Church. <hi>Behold how plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sant it is for Brethren to dwell together in Unity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And here let me speak one word to you who are Church-Wardens, and are entrusted with the care of Presenting Disorders to the Governours of the Church; to beseech you to consider the Religion and Sacredness of an Oath, which in the House of God, and as you expect help from God, you promise to perform; with the Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of which Oath and Fear of Gods dreadful Name,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:106773:28"/> were you so throughly affected, as indeed you ought, we should not see what with grief we do, so great Contempt of Gods House and Ordinances, as if they were common and prophane things; many scarce throughout the whole year making their Confession of sins to God in the As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sembly of his People, many seldom or never hearing one Psalm of <hi>David,</hi> or Chapter of the Holy Scriptures read unto them; nay, many neglecting the whole Liturgy of the Church, and dropping in after the Sermon is begun, and though the Preacher hath taken sad pains for what in the Name of God he speaks unto them, having not yet the patience to stay till that piece of the hour be ended. Certainly <hi>David</hi> had learned more Reverence to the Lords House, <hi>I was glad when they said, Let us go into the House of the Lord,</hi> Psal. 122. 1. and so had <hi>Cornelius,</hi> who with his Kindred and near Friends <hi>waited</hi> for the coming of <hi>Peter, Acts</hi> 10. 24. and so had <hi>Solomon,</hi> who teacheth men <hi>to watch daily at the Gates, and to give attendance at the Posts of the Doors of Gods House,</hi> Prov. 8. 34. And the Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies foretell the like of Gods people under the Gospel, that they should call upon one another, and should <hi>go speedily</hi> to pray before the Lord, and to seek the Lord, <hi>Zach.</hi> 8. 21. I speak this in Zele to the <hi>Service</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and to the <hi>Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence</hi> of his <hi>Sanctuary,</hi> and beseech you by the Sacredness of your Oath, and for the fear of Gods Name to think upon it. Thus far the Pious, Learned, and Reverend Dr. <hi>Reynolds</hi> (now Lord Bishop of <hi>Norwich)</hi> in that his Sermon at the <hi>Visitation.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:106773:28"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>